<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the wars in Ireland, betwixt Their Majesties army and the forces of the late King James Giving an impartial relation of all the battles, sieges, rencounters, skirmishes and other material passages, revolutions and accidents that has happened in that kingdom since the year 1688. The second edition, corrected. To which is added, the siege of Lymerick, to the raising thereof; with the siege and surrender of Bandon, Cork, the Old and New Fort, and town of Kin-sale; with other material occurrences. By an officer in the Royal Army. Illustrated with the lively effigies of His Sacred Majesty, and the great commanders in the Army.</title>
            <author>Officer in the Royal Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43956</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2190A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218430</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830029</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830029</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43956)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2031:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the wars in Ireland, betwixt Their Majesties army and the forces of the late King James Giving an impartial relation of all the battles, sieges, rencounters, skirmishes and other material passages, revolutions and accidents that has happened in that kingdom since the year 1688. The second edition, corrected. To which is added, the siege of Lymerick, to the raising thereof; with the siege and surrender of Bandon, Cork, the Old and New Fort, and town of Kin-sale; with other material occurrences. By an officer in the Royal Army. Illustrated with the lively effigies of His Sacred Majesty, and the great commanders in the Army.</title>
                  <author>Officer in the Royal Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 154 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Benj. Johnson, in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Engraved frontispiece is nine portraits, headed "Great Britains David &amp; his worthies".</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Price bound one shilling.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Gathered in sixes.</note>
                  <note>Copy has some print faded, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II,1685-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:34476:2"/>
            <head>Great Britains David &amp; His Worthies</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walker</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>Count Schonberg.</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>Col. Wolseley</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>Pr. of Denmark</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>King William III.</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>Duke Schonberg.</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>Count de Solmes.</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>L. Gen. Douglas.</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <figure>
                           <head>M. Gen. Kirk</head>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <l>These Worthies Nine them ſelve shall Eternize</l>
            <l>Their Acts one Volume could not well Comprize</l>
            <l>Mongst whom, Great William justly leads.</l>
            <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>'ve their Thousands he has ten thou. slain.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE Wars in Ireland, Betwixt Their Majeſties Army AND THE Forces of the late King Iames.</p>
            <p>GIVING An Impartial Relation of all the Battles, Sieges, Rencounters, Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, and other Material Paſſages, Revolutions and Accidents that has happened in that Kingdom ſince the Year 1688.</p>
            <p>The Second Edition, Corrected.</p>
            <p>To which is added, The Siege of <hi>Lymerick,</hi> to the Raiſing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; with the Siege and Surrender of <hi>Bandon, Cork,</hi> the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Fort,</hi> and Town of <hi>Kin-ſale;</hi> with other Material Occurrences.</p>
            <p>By an Officer in the Royal Army.</p>
            <p>Illuſtrated with the Lively Effigies of His Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the Great Commanders in the Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Johnſon,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi> 1691.</p>
            <p>Price Bound One Shilling.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34476:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:34476:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34476:3"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>World</hi> is grown ſo Nice and Critical up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Dedications</hi> and <hi>Prefaces,</hi> that it will needs be Judging the <hi>Book,</hi> by (what they call) the Wit of <hi>either;</hi> though the <hi>former</hi> are generally ſtuffed with fulſom <hi>Panegyricks,</hi> extolling the Vertues of ſome Grand <hi>Debauchee,</hi> or <hi>Leud Sinner</hi> of the Age; and the <hi>latter</hi> are filled up with <hi>Apologies</hi> to the <hi>Reader,</hi> pretending to give a Reaſon for the making their <hi>Work</hi> Publick; tho its not one time in a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,
<pb facs="tcp:34476:4"/>that the World has the true <hi>One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Matter</hi> herein contained, is <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH of Hiſtory,</hi> which requires no Apology; and, as ſuch, I do here preſent <hi>it</hi> to the World, without either <hi>Vanity,</hi> or <hi>Complement:</hi> Therefore, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a canting <hi>Preface,</hi> to fill a Vacancy, and pleaſe the <hi>Stationer,</hi> I have put the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents,</hi> or <hi>Table of Matters;</hi> whereby the <hi>Reader,</hi> may, at once, take a full view of what is contained in this <hi>Little Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:34476:4"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF THE MATTERS Contain'd in this BOOK.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TYrconnel</hi> made Lord Deputy. The Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Troubles. The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in general Diſarm'd, throughout <hi>Ireland.</hi> The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cut-Throats, Sons and Grand-Sons of the Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Forty One, Armed. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Clergy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſume their Biſhopricks and Livings. Notorious Abuſes committed on the <hi>Proteſtant</hi>-Clergy The Act of Settlement broken by the <hi>Paplſts</hi> in all parts of <hi>Ireland. Tyrconnel</hi> raiſes the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Raparees, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Late King's Abdieating the Goverment in <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> Arm. The Gates of <hi>London-Derry</hi> ſhut. Collonel <hi>Phillips</hi> made Governour. Then Collonel <hi>Lundy.</hi> The Men of <hi>Inniskilling, &amp;c.</hi> Aſſemble, and chooſe <hi>Guſtavus Hamilton,</hi> Eſp; their Governour. A mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Contract between <hi>Inniskilling</hi> and <hi>Derry.</hi> King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> Proclaimed at <hi>Inniskilling.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:34476:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. II</head>
               <p>CAptain <hi>Hamilton</hi> Arrives from the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Collonel <hi>Philips</hi> ſent to <hi>England</hi> for Aid. <hi>Cuningham</hi> and <hi>Richards</hi> Arrive in the <hi>Lough</hi> of <hi>Derry,</hi> with their Regiments. King <hi>James</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives with his Army before the Walls of <hi>Derry,</hi> ſuſpecting Treachery; the Army Fires their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non on them. Major <hi>Baker,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> choſe Governours of <hi>Derry.</hi> Siege of <hi>Crome</hi> raiſed by the Men of <hi>Inniskilling.</hi> The Two <hi>Mock Cannons</hi> taken. Collonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> takes the Caſtle of <hi>Augher.</hi> Collonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> Defeats a Body of the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> takes <hi>Mac Donel,</hi> their Commander, Priſoner. The ſtrong Caſtles of <hi>Redhil</hi> and <hi>Belliſhany</hi> taken by Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Lloyd.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>A Party of the Enemy at <hi>Derry</hi> march to <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nybourn-hill.</hi> Lord <hi>Strabane</hi> Summons the Town, but they return a Gallant Anſwer The Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers raiſe ſeveral Batteries, which are ſoon Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted by the Beſieged. The Beſieged make many ſucceſsful Sallies, killing multitudes of the Enemies. Major General <hi>Kirk,</hi> with 300 Sail Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive in the <hi>Lough</hi> of <hi>Derry.</hi> General <hi>Roſen</hi> and <hi>Hamilton</hi> make great Offers to the Gariiſon, are rejected. Great numbers of all ſorts of poor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants driven before the Walls. The Gariſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the laſt extremity. <hi>Derry</hi> relieved by <hi>Kirk,</hi> and the Siege raiſed; the numbers of Men killed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:34476:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Men purſue the Rear of the <hi>Derry Iriſh</hi> Army, takes 400 Horſes, and 300 Cows. The Town of <hi>Omagh</hi> Taken General <hi>Sarsfield</hi> and Collonel <hi>Southerland</hi> appears with 6000 Men. Collonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> Beſieges and takes <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbet.</hi> The Gariſon made Priſoners of War. A Meſſage from General <hi>Kirk</hi> to <hi>Inniskilling.</hi> A Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply from General <hi>Kirk,</hi> of Ammunition and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſent to <hi>Inniskilling.</hi> Collonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> Arrives in <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> Regiments the Forces there. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Mac Carty</hi> appears with his Army before the Town of <hi>Crom,</hi> raiſes Batteries againſt the Caſtle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>COllonel <hi>Berry</hi> Marches to Relieve <hi>Liſnaskea,</hi> and ſucceeds, Marches after the Enemy. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Berry</hi> Fights the Enemies Army, Commanded by Major General <hi>Alexander Hamilton</hi> Defeats them, kills 200 of the Enemy, takes 30 Priſoners Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> with 2000 <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Men, Fights <hi>Mac Carties</hi> Army of 6000, gives them a Total Rout, kill 3300 of the Enemy, takes <hi>Mac. Carty</hi> himſelf Priſoner, with all their Artillery, Arms, Baggage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>DUke <hi>Schonberg,</hi> with the Army, Embarks at <hi>Highlake,</hi> with Ninety Sail of Ships. Lands at <hi>Bangor.</hi> The Men lye on their Arms all Night. The Caſtle of <hi>Antrim</hi> Taken. The Enemy quits
<pb facs="tcp:34476:6"/>
                  <hi>Belfaſt. Carrick-fergus</hi> reſolves to make a reſolute Defence. The Duke in the Trenches. Batteries raiſed, and the Town Bombarded. Hot Firing on both ſides. Officers killed in the Trenches. The Famous Ingineer <hi>Richards</hi> carried out Wounded. The Town offers to Capitulate, and Surrenders up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Articles, after 20 days Siege. The Army De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camps, Marches to <hi>Newry;</hi> on the approach of whom, the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> Burns and quits the Place The Army Encamps on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>DUke <hi>Schonberg,</hi> on the Burning of the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſends a Trumpet to the Duke of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick.</hi> The Enemy quit <hi>Dundalk</hi> without Burning it. Our Army Encamp on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk.</hi> The Enemy about <hi>Ardee.</hi> Collonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> Defeats 5000 <hi>Iriſh</hi> near <hi>Slego,</hi> Kills 700, and takes 300 Priſoners, with their Commander. A Conſpiracy of <hi>French Papiſts</hi> diſcovered in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Camp. A Captain and Four others Hanged. 50 more ſent Priſoners to <hi>England.</hi> Collonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> with a Party of <hi>Inniskilling</hi>-Men, takes the Caſtle of <hi>Dramnaſna</hi> and <hi>James-Town.</hi> Great Mortality in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Camp, of which 15000 Die. Dake <hi>Schonberg</hi>'s Proclamation of Proviſions. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> March into Winter Quarters. <hi>James-Town</hi> quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The Fight at <hi>Slego,</hi> between Collonel <hi>Lloyd,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Officer, and <hi>Sarsfield.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army Decamp, and go into Winter Quarters. The Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Newry,</hi> between a Party of Collonel <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golsby</hi>'s, and 700 <hi>Iriſh.</hi> Collonel <hi>Cambon</hi>'s Action at <hi>Charlemont.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:34476:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Iriſh</hi> Defeated at the <hi>Newry,</hi> by Brigadeer <hi>Steward,</hi> 30 Killed, and 7 Taken Priſoners. Collonel <hi>Woolſely,</hi> takes <hi>Belturbet</hi> Lady <hi>Newcomens</hi> Houſe Surrendred. Duke <hi>Schonberg</hi> views <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont,</hi> and takes Booty under the Walls. Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Berry,</hi> and <hi>St. John,</hi> takes great Plunder. Duke <hi>Schonberg</hi>'s. Proclamation againſt Curſing and Swearing. Duke <hi>Schonberg</hi> with a Party goes to <hi>Dundalk.</hi> Collonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> Defeats the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> at <hi>Cavan,</hi> Kills 300, Takes great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Officers Priſoners, and 200 Common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. Brigadeer <hi>Nngent</hi> Mortally Wounded. Four Thouſand pound in Braſs-Money taken from the Rebels. Sir <hi>John Laneer</hi> takes <hi>Bedloe</hi> Caſtle. Prince <hi>Wirtenburgh</hi> and the <hi>Danes,</hi> Land at <hi>Belfaſt.</hi> The Famour Action of Mounſieur <hi>Callimate</hi> at <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont.</hi> 5000 <hi>French</hi> Land at <hi>Kingſale.</hi> Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Tryal at <hi>Lisburn,</hi> for the eſcape of General <hi>Mac-Carty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Cloveſly Shovel</hi> Arrives at <hi>Belfaſt</hi> with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Armes, and Ammunition for the Army. The Famous Action of Sir <hi>Cloveſly Shovel</hi> at the <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Dublin</hi> related. <hi>Charlemont</hi> Surprized by an Ambuſcade in the Night. The Governour of <hi>Charlemont</hi> demands a Party, and Surrenders <hi>May 13th.</hi> the Articles of Capitulation: The Duke views the Situation of <hi>Charlemont</hi> and the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon as they March out. <hi>May 15th.</hi> Collonel
<pb facs="tcp:34476:7"/>
                  <hi>Woolſely</hi> with Twelve Hundred Men Beſieges <hi>Bellin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garny,</hi> raiſes Works againſt it, and beats the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my from their Out Works. Preparations to Storm the Place. The Garriſon hang out a White Flag, and after Capitulates. The number Killed and Wounded in the Siege.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>BRief Accounts of the Transactions of the Late King <hi>James,</hi> towards the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The ſham Pardon of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Town of <hi>Bandon,</hi> and the Cruelty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards uſed towards them. The Transactions of the Earl of <hi>Seaforth.</hi> Sir <hi>R. Neagle,</hi> and Sir <hi>Tho. Southwel.</hi> Particular Cruilties towards the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> at <hi>Limerick</hi> and <hi>Dublin.</hi> The ſeveral ſham Proclamations to enſnare the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Invoice of the Proteſtants Goods ſeized in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſent to the <hi>French</hi> King. The Late King's ſeizing the Farmers Bread-Corn, to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſtarving of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Inhabitants. The Inhumane and Barbarous Uſage of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at <hi>Galway,</hi> by Order of the Late King. The Raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Farmers Daughter in <hi>Dublin,</hi> at Noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, before her Fathers Face. The Murthering three <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Clothiers in the Suburbs of <hi>Dublin.</hi> The Cruelties of the <hi>French</hi> towards the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:34476:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>GReat Plunder taken by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> near <hi>Finagh</hi> and <hi>Kells,</hi> 27 Miles of <hi>Dublin. Caſtle-Blany</hi> and ſeveral Villages burnt. The Rebels break down the Bridges between <hi>Newry</hi> and <hi>Dundalk.</hi> Duke <hi>Schonberg</hi> goes to <hi>Belfaſt</hi> the <hi>14th. June,</hi> expecting the King. <hi>June 15th.</hi> The King Lands at <hi>Carrick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fergus</hi> His great Reception in all Places, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral addreſſes preſented to him. <hi>June 24th.</hi> His Majeſty goes to <hi>Newry.</hi> A Camp is there form'd. The King's Meſſage to the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> The <hi>Iriſh</hi> quit <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and retires to <hi>Ardee.</hi> The whole <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Army Encamps on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk.</hi> The <hi>Iriſh</hi> quit <hi>Ardee,</hi> poſt themſelves on the <hi>Boyne. June 30th.</hi> the King Encamps within ſight of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, Is Wounded with a Cannon Ball, view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Enemies Camp. <hi>July 1ſt.</hi> Part of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Army paſſes the <hi>Boyne.</hi> The whole <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army Defeated, and retires after their King to <hi>Dublin.</hi> The Condition of <hi>Dublin</hi> on the Approach of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army. King <hi>James</hi> retires to <hi>Waterford.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army Encamp at <hi>Finglaſs,</hi> from whence the King goes to <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>THE Kingss Declaration, Pardoning the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Commonality. <hi>Cavan</hi> and <hi>Slego,</hi> Surrender. <hi>Longford,</hi> and Lord <hi>Longford</hi>'s Houſe Burnt. Earl <hi>Tyrone</hi> diſplaced at <hi>Waterford,</hi> and <hi>Lacy</hi> made Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. Four Hundred Head of Cattle taken from the Baparees. <hi>Clonmell</hi> quitted, and <hi>Sarſefield,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34476:8"/>with Five Thouſand Men, retires from before it, towards <hi>Lymerick. Waterford</hi> Summoned by the King, begins to Capitulate, Surrenders on Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Lord <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Howard</hi> Submit. <hi>Limerick</hi> poſſeſſed by the <hi>French.</hi> The King on His way for <hi>England,</hi> alters His Reſolutions. Captain <hi>Buck</hi> Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renders <hi>Duncannon. Douglas</hi> and <hi>Kirk,</hi> join the Army. <hi>Yaughall</hi> Surrendred. The Army before <hi>Lymerick.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34476:8"/>
            <head>The Hiſtory of The Wars in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> made Lord Deputy. The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Troubles. The <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> in general Diſarm'd, throughout <hi>Ireland.</hi> The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cut-Throats, Sons and Grand-Sons of the Maſſakers of Forty One, Armed. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Clergy re-aſſume their Biſhopricks and Livings. Notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Abuſes committed on the <hi>Proteſtant</hi>-Clergy. The Act of Settlement broken by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in all parts of <hi>Ireland. Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connel</hi> raiſes the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Raparees, upon the late King's Abdicating the Government in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> Arm. The Gates of <hi>London-Derry</hi> ſhut. Colonel <hi>Philips</hi> made Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor. Then Colonel <hi>Lundy.</hi> The Men of <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> &amp;c. Aſſemble, and chooſe <hi>Guſtavus Hamilton,</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr> their Governor. A mutual Contract between <hi>Inniskilling</hi> and <hi>Derry.</hi> King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> Proclaimed at <hi>Inniskilling.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE late King <hi>James,</hi> ſometime after his Acceſſion to the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown of theſe Kingdoms, ſending the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> his Deputy,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34476:9"/>into <hi>Ireland</hi> (an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt, and one who was known to be a mortal Hater of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt) the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in that Kingdom ſoon groaned under the Fears of approaching Miſeries, for he was ſcarce warm in his Place, before the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in general were Diſarm'd and Diſplac'd; many of them, after the moſt ſignal Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of their Fathers and themſelves to the Crown; and the Arms put into the hand of the Off-ſpring of the Bloody Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of <hi>Forty One;</hi> nay, not only the Off-ſpring, but many of the very hands that committed thoſe Maſſacres, were Arm'd by Authority, at the ſame time that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were thruſt out of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, on pretence that ſome one or other of their Relations had ingaged with the Uſurpers; tho' themſelves had ſerved the King to their utmoſt Extremities; and many were caſhiered, againſt whom even that pretence could not be found, and who had bought their Places with the King's Licenſe, and laid out all they had upon it; till at laſt, being a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> was given for the reaſon: And they were diſcouraged by all the Artifice of <hi>Jeſuit</hi> or <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and even threatn'd another Maſſacre, by many of their leſſer Polititians. All the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34476:9"/>and Livings that fell in the King's Gift, were kept Vacant, and the Revenues given to the Popiſh Clergy. Their Biſhops kept publick Viſitations in the Vacant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſes, and aſſumed even the Title; one of whom was made Secretary of State, and ſigned himſelf by the Name of his Biſhopricks in all his Warrants and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches, that none might plead Ignorance of the King's Intentions towards us. And we were told by ſome of the prime Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State, That the King would fill no <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Vacancies in the Church; ſo that we ſaw great part of the Churches in their Poſſeſſion, and nothing interpoſe for the remainder, but the Lives of the preſent Clergy. And for our Civil Rights, our Judges, Juſtices of the Peace, Sheriffs, and even Conſtables, were, for the moſt part, made of <hi>Papiſts:</hi> And the Act of Settlement was then doom'd in every <hi>Coffee-Houſe</hi> to the ſame condemnation under which it has fall'n ſince. And the Army being intirely in theſe worſt of Popiſh Hands, the moſt Barbarous <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who had thrown off Humanity it ſelf, our proſpect was all black and diſmal.</p>
               <p>In this condition we were in, when the news came that the late King <hi>James</hi> had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34476:10"/>voluntary thrown up his Government, Disbanded his Army, and was retired, ſome ſaid, to a Monaſtry, ſome to <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſome Dead, as every Man's Fancy led him; and which to believe we knew not.</p>
               <p>At this very time Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> Armed the Rabble of <hi>Iriſh Papiſts,</hi> to the number of 50 or 60 Thouſand, and to live upon the Country without Pay; whence enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed miſerable Depredations, open Noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Robberies, and an inevitable and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Ruine of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in <hi>Ireland;</hi> for many of theſe New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raiſed Men were ſo tranſported with the glorious Proſpect they had before them, that they had not the Continence, no, not their Prieſts, to refrain telling us, That they were now our Maſters, and we muſt ſubmit to new Laws. Then it was that we thought our ſelves no longer obliged to be active in our own Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>London-Derry</hi> and <hi>Inniskilling</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only Places (of any conſideration) in the Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer occaſioned by the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s being ſo infatuated, as that when the 3000 Men were ſent to <hi>England,</hi> to the Aſſiſtance of his Maſter, againſt the Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> He took
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34476:10"/>particular care to ſend away the White Remiment, Quartered in and about that City; but ſeeing his Etror, he endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to repair it, by commanding the Lord <hi>Antrim</hi> to Quarter there with his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſiſting of a numerous ſwarm of <hi>Iriſh</hi> and Highlanders, on the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 1688. this Regiment being on their <hi>March,</hi> the Citizens receiving ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of it by one Colonel <hi>George Philips;</hi> they, after ſeveral Conſultations reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhuts up their Gates, and choſe the ſaid Colonel their Governor; and diſpatches Mr. <hi>D. Kermes</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Proceedings. News being brought to <hi>Dublin</hi> of this Revolt (as they term'd it) the Lord <hi>Mountjoy,</hi> and Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Colonel <hi>Lundy,</hi> with Six Companies, are ſent down to reduce the place, who appearing before the Town, they let <hi>Mountjoy</hi> and <hi>Lundy</hi> in, on the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that only Two Companies of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment (and they all <hi>Proteſtants</hi>) ſhould enter with them, and that the Town Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, being Eight in number, ſhould be allowed to keep their Arms; the Lord <hi>Mountjoy</hi> made Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lundy</hi> their Governor.</p>
               <p>While theſe Affairs were carrying on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34476:11"/>at <hi>Derry</hi> for their own Defence, the Men of <hi>Inniskilling</hi> were not Idle. On the ſecond of <hi>December,</hi> 1688. there came a Letter from Mr. Secretary <hi>Ellis,</hi> by the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s Order, to the Provoſt of <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> to provide Quarters for Two Foot Companies. Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> the 15. of <hi>December</hi> the Two Foot Companies came to <hi>Mac Guires</hi> Bridge, within Eight ſhort Miles of the Town; and upon <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> about Ten a Clock, word was brought us, that they were within Four Miles, at which time moſt of the Men were at Church, but they ſoon came out and Armed themſelves; being drawn out, they were about 200 Foot, and 150 Horſe, and having conſulted Matters, they ſent ſome of their Number to perſwade them by fair means to return: And at the ſame time <hi>Guſtavus Hamilton,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> our preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, came with about 100 Horſe, within a Mile of the Town, to ſupport it if there ſhould be occaſion; Our Horſe, under the Command of Captain <hi>Browning,</hi> and Lieutenant <hi>Carleton;</hi> and the Foot under the Command of Captain <hi>Catheart,</hi> advancing towards the Enemy, they no ſooner came within View, but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy immediately fled, and the next
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34476:11"/>day got to <hi>Cavan,</hi> 24 Miles from <hi>Innis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing.</hi> About the <hi>18th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> the Men of <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> and their Adherents, ſeeing <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> Arming the <hi>Iriſh</hi> on all Hands, thought it adviſable to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſome Poſture of Defence; and at a full meeting, unanimouſly choſe <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtavus Hamilton</hi> their Governor, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of a great Family, and as great Courage, he conſented to take the charge upon him, who (beſides Two Foot Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies to be raiſed in and about the Town) formed a good Troop of Horſe, and a Foot Company, out of his own Eſtate, and the Country adjoyning. Sometime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Men of <hi>Inniskilling</hi> hearing that <hi>Derry</hi> had denied Entrance to the Lord <hi>Antrim</hi>'s Regiment, and were putting themſelves into a poſture of Defence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any <hi>Iriſh</hi> Garriſon to be ſent there, which clearly reſembled their own caſe. On the <hi>20th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> they ſent Capt. <hi>Cathcart,</hi> and Lieutenant <hi>Mac Cormick,</hi> to acquaint the Garriſon with what they had done, craving their advice and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in caſe of any Trouble, promiſing the ſame to them, if they ſtood in need of it; to which Meſſage the Men of <hi>Derry</hi> ſent a very kind return by thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34476:12"/>that were ſent. The Month of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> was ſpent at <hi>Inniskilling</hi> in raiſing more Troops and Companies. The Month of <hi>February</hi> was ſpent in Conſultations with Colonel <hi>Lundy,</hi> and the leading Men in the Counties of <hi>Derry, Dunegal, Tyrone, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van,</hi> and elſe-where.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 11. King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> were Proclaimed with much Joy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 20. Upon the Lord <hi>Gilmoy</hi>'s coming with part of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army into the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> the ſeveral Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there, with all the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (being ordered by Colonel <hi>Lundy</hi>) left the places, and came running to <hi>Inniskilling;</hi> the ſame Colonel <hi>Lundy</hi> did endeavour to perſwade the Governor of <hi>Inniskilling</hi> to do the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34476:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Captain <hi>Hamilton</hi> Arrives from the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Colonel <hi>Philips</hi> ſent to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for Aid. <hi>Cunningham</hi> and <hi>Richards</hi> Arrive in the <hi>Lough</hi> of <hi>Derry,</hi> with their Regiments. King <hi>James</hi> Arrives with his Army before the Walls of <hi>Derry,</hi> ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting Treachery; the Army Fires their Cannon on them. Major <hi>Baker,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> choſe Governors of <hi>Derry.</hi> Siege of <hi>Crome</hi> raiſed by the Men of <hi>Inniskilling.</hi> The Two <hi>Mack Cannons</hi> taken. Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> takes the Caſtle of <hi>Augher.</hi> Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> Defeats a Body of the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> takes <hi>Mac Donel,</hi> their Commander, Priſoner. The ſtrong Caſtles of <hi>Redhil</hi> and <hi>Belli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhany</hi> taken by Colonel <hi>Lloyd.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ON the <hi>21ſt</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> Captain <hi>J. Hamilton</hi> Arrived from <hi>England,</hi> in the <hi>Lough</hi> of <hi>Derry,</hi> with Ammunition and Arms, 480 Barrels of Powder, and Arms for 2000 Men, and aſſurance of more Supplies; he likewiſe brought a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the King and Queen for <hi>Lundy</hi> to be Governor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 23. Colonel <hi>Philips</hi> is ſent from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34476:13"/>
                  <hi>Derry</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> to ſolicite a ſpeedy Supply.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 15. 1689. Colonel <hi>Cunningham</hi> and Colonel <hi>Richards</hi> came into the <hi>Lough</hi> from <hi>England,</hi> with Two Regiments, and other Neceſſaries for <hi>Derry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 17. Upon the News of K. <hi>James</hi>'s Army being on their March towards <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-Derry,</hi> Colonel <hi>Lundy</hi> immediately calls a Council and that Colonel <hi>Richards</hi> and <hi>Cunningham</hi> ſhould be Members of it, accordingly they met; but being Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men wholly unacquainted with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Town, they make an Order that the Two Regiments that <hi>Richards</hi> and <hi>Cunningham</hi> had brought with them ſhould not be Landed: That the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and principal Officers ſhould private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withdraw themſelves from the Town, that the Inhabitants, by a timely Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, may make the better Terms with the Enemy.</p>
               <p>After this Reſolution, an Inſtrument was prepared to be ſent to King <hi>James,</hi> who was advanced in Perſon with his Army as far as St. <hi>John's-Town;</hi> but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Gentlemen of the Garriſon did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe to ſubſcribe, but expreſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with threatnings to Hang the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34476:13"/>and his Council; but yet the Council ſent one Captain <hi>White</hi> to the late King.</p>
               <p>Upon the <hi>18th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> the late King advanced with his Army before the Walls of <hi>Derry,</hi> with Flying Colours: And Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were given by the Council, That none ſhould dare Fire till the King's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands were firſt known; but the Men on the Walls wondring to ſee Lieutenant General <hi>Hamilton</hi> (contrary to his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with <hi>White,</hi> not to come within Four Miles) approach their Walls, they imagined they were Betrayed, thought it reaſonable to conſider their own Safety, and ſo immediately Fired the Guns on the Enemy.</p>
               <p>The Enemy being great Strangers to this ſort of Exerciſe, ran away: A great many were Killed: King <hi>James,</hi> in ſome diſorder, retired with his Army to St. <hi>John's Town;</hi> in the mean time the Town-Clerk informed the Inhabitants of the whole Proceeding of the Council of War, which very much enraged them.</p>
               <p>The Governor and his Council thinking themſelves in danger, from the Citizens, make their private eſcape to the Ships in the River at <hi>Kilmore,</hi> tho' not without hazzard.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34476:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>April 19th</hi> the Garriſon ſeeing they were Deſerted, and left without a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and having unanimouſly reſolved to defend the Town againſt the Enemy, they unanimouſly choſe Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> and Major <hi>Baker,</hi> their Governors, who having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the Government of the Garriſon; theſe Gentlemen choſe Eight Colonels, and Regimented the Men, which, on the Muſter, were 7020 Men, 341 Officers; they then viewed the Stores, and gave all neceſſary Orders.</p>
               <p>But to return again to the Men of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niskilling,</hi> the Lord <hi>Gilmoy</hi> thinking to perſwade the whole Country to do as thoſe about <hi>Cavan</hi> had done. On the 21. of <hi>March</hi> he came to <hi>Belturbet,</hi> and the next day ſent a Party to <hi>Crom,</hi> to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege it with Two Mock Cannon made with Tin; He Summons the place, but to no purpoſe; and the next day being the 22. he ſent a Letter to the Governor of <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> in the nature of a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; but the Governor and Garriſon reſolved not to ſubmit to any but King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> The <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> the Governor ſent 200 of his beſt Men to relieve <hi>Crom,</hi> who, after ſome Oppoſition, got into the Caſtle by Water;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34476:14"/>and having joyned thoſe that were within, Sallied out, and raiſed the Siege, beating them from their Trenches, Killed between 30 and 40, took many Arms, with their Two Mock Cannon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 25. 1689. Having Intelligence that Captain <hi>J. Hamilton</hi> was Arrived at <hi>Derry</hi> with ſtore of Ammunition and Arms, the Governor of <hi>Inniskilling</hi> ſent Two Gentlemen, with a Guard, with Letters to Colonel <hi>Lundy</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hamilton</hi> for a ſupply of Arms and Ammunition the latter was very willing to ſupply us, but Colonel <hi>Lundy</hi> having the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, would not give us one fixed Arm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 13. By the Procurement of Mr. <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Inſtructions were ordered on both ſides, That if at <hi>Inniskilling</hi> it was reported that <hi>Derry</hi> was Taken, they ſhould not believe it, unleſs they receiv'd it from Colonel <hi>Walker</hi>'s own Hand; and if at <hi>Derry</hi> it was reported, at any time, That <hi>Inniskilling</hi> was Taken, they ſhould not believe it, unleſs it came from under Governor <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s one Hand; and this was very happily concluded on, for there was ſcarce a Week, after the Siege of <hi>Derry</hi> began, but the <hi>Iriſh</hi> got means to ſpread a Report, That <hi>Derry</hi> or <hi>Inniskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:34476:15"/>were taken, a Stratagem to diſhearten the Garriſon of both places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 24. Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyd,</hi> with a Party of Horſe and Foot, march'd out of <hi>Inniskilling</hi> to <hi>Angher,</hi> where the Garriſon fled before he came there: He cauſed the Caſtle to be Burnt, leaſt the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſhould return: He returned by the way of <hi>Moneghan</hi> to <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> with a very great Booty of <hi>Cows</hi> and <hi>Sheep,</hi> &amp;c. which came very ſeaſonably. At this time there came to <hi>Inniskilling</hi> from <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhany,</hi> ſome Troops and Foot Companies of excellent Men, of the Lord <hi>Kingston</hi>'s: And then Governor <hi>Hamilton</hi> raiſed a Fort on the common Hill, next the <hi>Stone-Bridge,</hi> which is now of very conſiderable ſtrength, and great ſecurity to the Town.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May</hi> 4. The Governor had an Expreſs ſent him from Captain <hi>Falliot,</hi> Governor of <hi>Belliſhany,</hi> acquainting him that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Party of Men were come to Beſiege that place, and deſired Relief: Governor <hi>Hamilton</hi> immediately drew out of the ſeveral Garriſons under his Command, what Men he could ſpare; and the next day ſent Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> with 12 Foot Companies, and ſome Troops of Horſe, towards <hi>Belliſhany,</hi> who
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34476:15"/>meeting the Enemies Horſe near <hi>Baleek,</hi> a Village three Miles nearer <hi>Inniskilling</hi> than <hi>Belliſhany,</hi> and after an Engagement, ſoon put them to the Rout, Killed about 120 of them, and took 60 Priſoners: All their Foot fled away over the Bogs, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Sligoe,</hi> and got off ſafe, except ſome few that were taken in the Fiſh-Iſlands near <hi>Belliſhany,</hi> with their Captain <hi>Mack Donagh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the latter end of <hi>May,</hi> Information came to <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> that <hi>Red-hill</hi> and <hi>Bellinacareg,</hi> in the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> were Garriſon'd by the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> was immediately diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt them; but he no ſooner ſet out with about 1500 Horſe and Foot; but the News of his March was brought to the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> before him; upon which all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Fled, and he no ſooner came to <hi>Red-hill,</hi> but the Garriſon held a ſign for a Treaty, and having Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons immediately Surrendred the Place, with all that was in it; from thence they marched to a very ſtrong place, called <hi>Bellinacareg;</hi> but the news of the Taking of <hi>Red-hill,</hi> ſtruck ſo great a Terror in thoſe of the Caſtle, that, in a little time after we came before it, they held out a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34476:16"/>White Flag for Treaty, and did capitulate, leaving the Arms and Ammunition, and what Goods were in the Caſtle to the Plunder of the Soldiers. The news of the taking of <hi>Red-hill</hi> and <hi>Bellinacareg,</hi> was ſoon brought to <hi>Dublin,</hi> with a Report that the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Army was Marching thither; being ever after this reputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to be above 15000 well Armed Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:34476:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A Party of the Enemy at <hi>Derry</hi> march to <hi>Pennybourn-Hill.</hi> Lord <hi>Strabane</hi> Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons the Town, but they return a Gallant Anſwer. The Beſiegers raiſe ſeveral Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, which are ſoon Diſmounted by the Beſieged. The Beſieged make many ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Sallies, killing multitudes of the Enemies. Major General <hi>Kirk,</hi> with <hi>30</hi> Sail Arrive in the <hi>Lough</hi> of <hi>Derry.</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Roſen</hi> and <hi>Hamilton</hi> make great Offers to the Garriſon, are rejected. Great numbers of all ſorts of poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> driven before the Walls. The Garriſon reduced to the laſt extremity. <hi>Derry</hi> relieved by <hi>Kirk,</hi> and the Siege raiſed; the numbers of Men killed.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AND now to return to the Affairs of <hi>Derry, April</hi> 20. A part of the Enemy marched to <hi>Penybourn-Hill,</hi> Two Mile from the Town, and pitched their Tents; the ſame day the Lord <hi>Strabane,</hi> and after him ſeveral Trumpets, came to the Walls to offer Propoſals, but the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon would not hear of any.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 21. The Enemy Planted a Demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culverin
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34476:17"/>180 Perches from the Town: The ſame day the Beſieged Sallied out, and Killed 200 of the Enemy, and <hi>Mamoe</hi> the <hi>French</hi> General.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 23. The Beſiegers Planted Four Demi-culverins in <hi>Strong</hi>'s Orchard, 80 Perches from the Town, and Played in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 28. The Beſieged made another Sally, and Killed many.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May</hi> 5. This Night the Beſiegers make a Battery on the <hi>Windmil-Hill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May</hi> 6. The Beſieged reſolved to ruine that Battery, and, in order thereunto, make a Sally, which Governor <hi>Walker</hi> heads; and they (with a great Slaughter) beat the Enemy from their Trenches, and ruined their new Works: In this Action 500 of the Enemy were Killed, and 200 Wounded: After this the Enemy were ſo daunted, that for ſeveral Weeks they lay ſtill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> 4. The Beſiegers make an Attack at the <hi>Windmil</hi>-Works, and our Men put themſelves in a readineſs to receive them: The Enemy came on, after the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> mode, with moſt dreadful ſhrieks from moſt parts of their Camp, and the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Rabble that attended them, but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34476:17"/>they, in a very little time, betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their old defence, and ran for it, not being able to ſtand our Firing.</p>
               <p>The Enemy, in this Action, loſt 400 of their Fighting Men, and moſt of their Officers: This Night, and the next day, the Enemy, from <hi>Strong</hi>'s Orchard, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Playing their Bombs, which were 273 pound weight apiece, which tore up the Streets, and beat down the Houſes, and Killed many People.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> 15. We diſcovered a Fleet of 30 Sail of Ships in the <hi>Lough,</hi> which proved to be Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> from <hi>England;</hi> but they could neither come nor ſend to us, nor we to them, for ſome time, by reaſon of a Boom lay'd a croſs the River, guarded by Two Forts on each ſide: At laſt, by means of a Boy, a correſpondence was kept, by which we gave the Major General an account of the condition of the Garriſon; and he promiſed to Relieve the Garriſon, either by way of the River, or Land, coſt him what it would. In <hi>June Conrad de Roſen,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Marſh. General and Lieutenant General <hi>Hamilton,</hi> at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, make great offers, if they would Surrender the Garriſon, and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Threats if they refuſed, which was ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34476:18"/>far from availing any thing, that an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was made to make it preſent Death to mention a Surrender.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> 30. Governor <hi>Baker</hi> dyes, very much lamented.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 2. The Enemy drive a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (according to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer threatnings) under the Walls, which the Beſieged perceiving, immediately (in ſight of their Camp) erect a Gallows, and ſignified to them, they were reſolved to hang their Friends, that were their Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, if they did not ſuffer thoſe poor Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to return to their own Houſes; and upon earneſt ſolicitations of the Priſoners, the poor People were removed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 25. The Beſieged made a Sally with 400 Men, and ſurpriſed the Enemy in their Trenches, Killed 300 of their Men, beſides Officers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 27. The Garriſon is reduced to 4456 Men, and under the greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of Famine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 30. About an hour after Sermon, being in the midſt of our extremity, we ſaw ſome Ships in the <hi>Lough</hi> make to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us; and we ſoon diſcovered Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> had ſent them, according to his Promiſe, when we could hold out
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34476:18"/>no longer. They were Two Ships with Proviſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>Dartmouth</hi> Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate. The Enemy Fired moſt deſperately upon them, from the Fort of <hi>Culmore,</hi> and both ſides the River; and they made ſufficient returns with the greateſt Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very: The <hi>Mountjoy,</hi> one of the Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, made a great ſtop at the Boom, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by her Rebound, after ſtriking and breaking it: Upon this the Enemy ſet up the loudeſt Huzza's, and the moſt dreadful to the Beſieged that ever they heard; Fired all their Guns upon her, and were preparing their Boats to Board her; but, by great Providence, firing a Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, the ſhock looſened her, ſo that ſhe got clear, and paſſed the Boom; and at length all the Ships got to them, to the unexpreſſible Joy and tranſport of the whole Garriſon, for they only reckoned on Two days Life, having only 9 Horſes leſt: Hunger and the fateague of War had ſo prevailed in the Town, that of 7500 Men Regimented, we had now alive but 4300.</p>
               <p>This brave undertaking, added to the great Succeſs <hi>God</hi> had bleſſed them in all their undertaking, and ſo dicouraged the Enemy, that, on the laſt of <hi>July,</hi> they ran
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34476:19"/>away in the Night time, Robb'd and Burnt all before them for ſeveral Miles, leaving nothing with the Country People, but what they hid the Night before.</p>
               <p>Thus, after 105 days being cloſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, by near 20000 Men, conſtantly ſupplied from <hi>Dublin,</hi> God Almighty was pleaſed, in the greateſt Extremity, to ſend Relief.</p>
               <p>The Enemy loſt about 9000 Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Walls, and 100 of their beſt Officers, from <hi>April</hi> 24. to <hi>July</hi> 22. Five Hundred Eighty ſeven Bombs were thrown into the City.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34476:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Men purſue the Rear-of the <hi>Derry Iriſh</hi> Army, takes <hi>400</hi> Horſes, and <hi>300</hi> Cows. The Town of <hi>Omagh</hi> Taken. General <hi>Sarsfield</hi> and Colonel <hi>Southerland</hi> appears with <hi>6000</hi> Men. Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> Beſieges and takes <hi>Beltur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</hi> The Garriſon made Priſoners of War. A Meſſage from General <hi>Kirk</hi> to <hi>Innis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing.</hi> A Supply from General <hi>Kirk,</hi> of Ammunition and Officers ſent to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niskilling.</hi> Colonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> Arrives in <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> Regiments the Forces there. General <hi>Mac Carty</hi> appears with his Army before the Town of <hi>Crom,</hi> raiſes Batteries againſt the Caſtle.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BUT to return to the Actions of the Men of <hi>Inniskilling: June</hi> 3. Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was brought to <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army before <hi>Derry,</hi> had ſent a great many of their Troops Horſes to Graze near <hi>Armagh,</hi> Eight Miles from us: The Governor, the next day, ſent Two Troops, and ordered them to ſtay at <hi>Trellick;</hi> they had not ſtaid there above Two days, when taken with them ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34476:20"/>Troop, and Two foot Companies, they went in the Evening towards <hi>Omagh,</hi> and before Eight a Clock the next day, they returned to <hi>Trellick</hi> with near 200 Horſes belonging to the Enemies Tooops, and near as many more ſmaller Horſes fit for Labour, and about 300 Cows; by this we did diſable at leaſt Three Troops of the Enemy, and Mounted many of our Men. Soon after hearing that <hi>Derry</hi> muſt Surrender very ſoon, unleſs Relieved, and believing that much of our ſafety did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon it, the Governor of <hi>Inniskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> reſolved in Perſon, with all the ſtrength he could make, to endeavour its Relief, or Periſh in the Attempt; and having drawn all his Men into the Field, being about 2000, on the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> he Marched to <hi>Trellick,</hi> and the next Night came near <hi>Omagh</hi> and by Morning poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed themſelves of the whole Town; but they had not been here many hours, but ſeveral Expreſſes came from <hi>Innis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing</hi> to the Governor and Officers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming that Colonel <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> with near 6000 Men was come to Beſiege <hi>Belliſhany,</hi> 20 Miles from <hi>Inniskilling;</hi> and that Col. <hi>Sowtherland</hi> was come to <hi>Belturbet,</hi> the ſame diſtance from <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> on the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34476:20"/>other hand; and that one or both the Armies would be very ſoon at <hi>Inniskilling;</hi> on which a Council of War was called, and it was reſolved, we ſhould return to the defence of <hi>Inniskilling;</hi> but they were ever reſolv'd not to ſuffer the Enemy to come ſo near them, as to lay Siege to the Town; and therefore the Governor or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> to take the Field with the greateſt Strength we could make in Foot and Horſe, and march againſt <hi>Southerland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> 17. Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> came with his Men to <hi>Mac Guires</hi> Bridge, a place not full half way betwixt <hi>Inniskilling</hi> and <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbet;</hi> from which place the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſpy went in the Night, and acquainted Col. <hi>Southerland,</hi> That all the Forces of <hi>Innis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing</hi> were coming againſt him; when this news was brought to <hi>Southerland,</hi> and he believing former Reports, That <hi>Inniskilling</hi> were 15000 Strong, he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately retired towards <hi>Charlemont,</hi> leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 80 Dragoons, and about 200 Foot, in the Church of <hi>Belturbet,</hi> to ſee if they could make good the Place againſt the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Men, until he could get force enough for their Relief: Our Men being got to <hi>Belturbet,</hi> the Enemy Fired very
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34476:21"/>faſt at us, but with their uſual Succeſs; we had not Attackt the place above Two hours, but they offered to Capitulate, it being agreed, That all the Officers and Soldiers ſhould be our Priſoners: There were Thirteen Commiſſion Officers, and Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Scot,</hi> their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander; we got likewiſe 700 Muſquets, a Barrel and half of Powder, ſeveral Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and 20 Horſe Load of Biſquets, 100 Barrels of Wheat, 50 of Flower, and near 300 common Soldiers Priſoners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 3. A Letter came from <hi>Belliſhany</hi> to <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> ſignifying that Captain <hi>Hobſon,</hi> with the <hi>Bonaventure</hi> Frigate was there, ſent from Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> at the <hi>Lough</hi> of <hi>Derry,</hi> to know their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and if they wanted any Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was a very acceptable Meſſage.</p>
               <p>The Governor ordered, that very night, Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyd,</hi> and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to take ſome Troops and March the next day towards <hi>Belliſhany;</hi> and the day following being the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> the Officers went on Board, where they were Treated with great Civility, by Captain <hi>Hobſon;</hi> &amp; they fully informing him of the ſtate of their Affairs, he gave good encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34476:21"/>aſſuring, that very ſoon there would care be taken to Relieve them: He gave them 30 Barrels of Powder, which the Officers, within Two days, ſent ſafe to <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> and Two of the number went back in the <hi>Bonadventure,</hi> with a Meſſage to Major General <hi>Kirk,</hi> for Commiſſions (to regulate the Men not diſciplin'd) ſome more Ammunition and Arms, and ſome Officers; who, on the <hi>12th</hi> came to the General in <hi>Derry Lough,</hi> where he lay with the Fleet: He, for about two days, did inform himſelf, by them, of the condition <hi>Inniskilling</hi> was in, what ſtore of Men belong'd to that Garriſon, and how Arm'd. They had then about 27 Troops, 30 Foot Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and ſome few Troops of Dragoons; the Foot were indifferently well Armed, but the Horſe and Dragoons not ſo well. The Major General had few Arms fit for Horſe, but he gave them 600 Fire-looks for Dragoons, 1000 Muſquets to raiſe more Foot, with 20 more Barrels of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, with Bullets and Match, Eight ſmall Canon, and ſome Hand-Granado's; He ſent likewiſe Commiſſions for a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Horſe, conſiſting of 16 Troops, 50 Men in each Troop; for a Regiment
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34476:22"/>of Dragoons, conſiſting of 12 Troops, 50 Men in each Troop; and for Three Regiments of Foot, 18 Companies in each, Two whereof to be Granadeers, 60 Men in each Company; and one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant Troop of Horſe to each Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Major General gave them ſome very good Officers, <hi>viz.</hi> Colonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> to be Commander in chief, and Colonel of Horſe; and Captain <hi>Berry,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel, Captain <hi>Stone</hi> Major; Captain <hi>Win</hi> to be Colonel of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons; and for our Three Regiments of Foot, <hi>Guſtavus Hamilton,</hi> the Governor of <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> was made firſt Colonel, and Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lloyd,</hi> and Major <hi>Tiffin,</hi> the other Two. And they being thus furniſhed according to deſire, they took leave of the Major General, <hi>Sunday</hi> the <hi>20th</hi> of <hi>July;</hi> but, through contrary Winds, came not to <hi>Belliſhany</hi> till <hi>Friday</hi> the <hi>26th,</hi> where they were no ſooner come, but notice was given them, that Lieutenant General <hi>Macarty,</hi> with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Army, was come to <hi>Belturbet,</hi> in order to Beſiege <hi>Inniskilling:</hi> Upon this, the Officers went the next day to <hi>Baleek;</hi> and on <hi>Sunday</hi> the 28. went from thence by Water, and Landed ſafe at <hi>Inniskilling,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:34476:22"/>and were receiv'd with ſome Ceremony, and great Rejoycings. That Night ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice came, That Lieutenant General <hi>Macarty</hi> was before <hi>Crom,</hi> and was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a Battery againſt the Caſtle: Upon which Colonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> made all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition poſſible, to get together what Forces he could, in order to Relieve them, and ſent for part of the Forces from <hi>Belliſhany;</hi> but <hi>Mac Carty</hi> marches towards <hi>Liſnaskeae.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Colonel <hi>Berry</hi> Marches to Relieve <hi>Liſnaskea,</hi> and ſucceeds, Marches after the Enemy. Colonel <hi>Berry</hi> Fights the Enemies Army, Commanded by Major General <hi>Alexander Hamilton,</hi> Defeats them, kills <hi>200</hi> of the Enemy, and takes <hi>30</hi> Priſoners. Colonel <hi>Woolſely.</hi> with <hi>2000 Inniskilling</hi> Men, Fights <hi>Mac Carties</hi> Army of <hi>6000,</hi> gives them a Total Rout, kills <hi>3300</hi> of the Enemy, takes <hi>Mac Carty</hi> himſelf Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with all their Artillery, Arms, Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN formation being brought, That a part of <hi>Mac Carties</hi> Army was marching
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34476:23"/>towards <hi>Liſnaskea,</hi> within 10 Miles of us: Upon this, Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Berry,</hi> the next Morning, being <hi>July</hi> 30, was ſent with Eight Troops of Horſe, Three Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Foot, and Two Troops of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, with order to get to the Caſtle of <hi>Liſnaskea</hi> before the Enemy, and to place a Garriſon in it, if he found it Tenable, otherwiſe to Burn it: But when he came there, he found the place of no conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and ſo left it. The next day, being the laſt of <hi>July,</hi> he marched his Men towards the Enemy (who lay about Six Miles from him): he had not march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above Two Miles, when, near a place called <hi>Donagh,</hi> his Scouts did diſcover a conſiderable Body of Horſe, Foot, and Dragoons; who immediately advertiſe Colonel <hi>Berry</hi> of their approach, who Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats with his Men towards <hi>Lisnaskea</hi> again; and in the way, on a riſing ground, had a full view of the Enemy, and found them above double the number of his own; on which he ſends an Expreſs to Colonel <hi>Wooſely</hi> at <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> for Relief; and Retreats about a Mile from <hi>Lisnas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kea,</hi> by a by-road, where coming to a Bog, with a narrow ſhort Cauſe-way through it, that ſcarce Two Horſemen
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34476:23"/>could ride a Breaſt; at the end of this Cauſe-way <hi>Berry</hi> halted, reſolving to make good that Paſs againſt the Enemy, till he ſhould be Relieved: There was a Thicket of Underwood juſt by the Cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, where the Foot were placed; the Horſe a little farther off, and gave the word <hi>Oxford:</hi> They made but a very ſhort ſtay there, when Colonel <hi>A. Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, (Mac Carty</hi>'s Major General) came in view with a conſiderable Body of Men, who alighting from his Horſe, ordered his Dragoons to do ſo to, and very brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advanced near the end of the Cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, his Men firing briskly at ours, but with little Succeſs; for they only wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome ſour or five of our Men: But ours were better Markſmen, they ſhot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a dozen Men dead at the end of the Cauſe-way, and wounded Colonel <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> their Leader, who being wounded, retreated, and ordered another Officer to lead on the Men, who was immediately Killed, with ſome more of the Men, which the Enemy perceiving, and having no one to lead them on, began to Retreat from the end of the Cauſe-way, which our Men ſeeing, gave a Huzza, and cryed out, <hi>The Rogues are running;</hi> and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34476:24"/>our Foot and Dragoons took the Bog on each hand, and our Horſe advanced on the Cauſe-way towards them; which the Enemy perceiving, began at firſt to retreat a little faſter from us; but their Retreat ſoon turned to a moſt diſorderly Flight, without offering to face about, or Fire any more at us; our Horſe ſoon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-took them, and fell in among their Foot, and ſuch Dragoons as were on foot, and made a very great Slaughter of them, having the chaſe of them through the Town of <hi>Liſnaskea,</hi> and near a Mile far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the Execution had been greater, but notice was brought to <hi>Berry,</hi> That Lieut. General <hi>Mac Carty,</hi> with the Body of his Army was advancing towards him: Upon this he ſounds a Retreat, and brings back his Men to the place where the Fight firſt began, having Killed about 200, and taken 30 Priſoners, with a great quantity of Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This happened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Nine in the Morning.</p>
               <p>About 12 of the Clock the ſame day, there came an Expreſs from Colonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> to Lieut. Colonel <hi>Berry,</hi> deſiring him to March his Party to <hi>Lisnaskea,</hi> where he would meet him, with the reſt of the Army, at the Moat of the Town,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34476:24"/>where, in a little time, they both met: Colonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> acquainted the Officers, That the Party under his Command had marched in ſuch great haſt to Relieve their Brethren, that they had ſcarce brought a Meals Meat with them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be reſolved, either immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to go Fight <hi>Mac Carty,</hi> or elſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Inniskilling</hi> again; the former of which was reſolved on, by the unanimous conſent of all the Soldiers. Upon this Colonel <hi>Woolſely,</hi> and the other Colonels, drew up all the Men in Battalia, and gave them the word <hi>No Popery;</hi> and then drew out four Men out of every Troop, with an Officer to Command them, for a <hi>Forlorn:</hi> Our whole Number, when all were joyned, conſiſted but of 2000 Men, or ſomething upwards.</p>
               <p>The Forlorn Colonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> ordered to March on about half a Mile before the Army: We had not marched a Mile from <hi>Donagh,</hi> when our <hi>Forlorn</hi> came in view of the <hi>Forlorn</hi> of the Enemy, who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately retreated before our Men; we advanced after them, till we came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in half a Mile of <hi>Newtown-Butler,</hi> where is a large Bog, and a little beyond a ſteep Hill, where the Enemy were drawn up
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34476:25"/>advantagiouſly. After our Men had paſt the Bog in good order, and came up to the Enemy, within Musket-ſhot, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Fire at us, but before Three Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies had been diſcharged on each ſide, our Men ſaw them begin to draw off, and Retreat, which they miſapprehending, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved them running away, and our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers had much ado to keep them from purſuing with what ſpeed they could: But Colonel <hi>Woolſely,</hi> from a Hill, ſaw them go off in ſo good order, that he believed it was either to draw our Men into an Ambuſh, or elſe Poſt themſelves to better Advantage; therefore ſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, That no Man ſhould go out of his Rank, but purſue them in good Order: Thus the Enemy retreated in good Order, and our Men after them, a Mile beyond <hi>Newtown-Butler,</hi> where they came to a Hill, juſt above a Bog, much ſuch a place as before, having their Cannon placed at the end of the Cauſe-way; Colonel <hi>Berry</hi> and Major <hi>Stone</hi> advanced with the Horſe to the Cauſe-way, but the Enemy plied their Canon ſo hard, that the Horſe could not Advance, but our Foot and Dragoons advanced on both ſides, through the Bog, (the Enemy ſtill keeping their Ground)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34476:25"/>till at laſt they came up and ſeized their Cannon, and Killed their Canoneers, and then advanced towards the Body of their Men, that were drawn up a little above them: As ſoon as our Horſe perceived their Canon were ſecured by our Foot, they advanced over the Cauſe-way, which the Enemies Horſe perceiving, they, with the mounted Dragoons, wheeled, and fled towards <hi>Wattle-Bridge,</hi> deſerting their Foot: Their Foot ſtood their Ground till our Men came among them; but then perceiving their own Horſe and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons fled, and ours coming up to them, they thought it no time to ſtay any longer, but turned their backs, and inſtead of going to the left-hand, where they had an open Country, fled all to the right, where they had a great Bog (which they ran through) for above a Mile, leading to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Loghearn;</hi> moſt of them throwing away their Arms into Turf-pits: Our Horſe followed theirs in a String, over the narrow ways, from the place where the Enemy had planted their Cannon to <hi>Wattle-Bridge,</hi> and left a good Guard of Horſe there, to ſecure the Paſs. Our Horſe kept all the Road between the Two places, that not one of their Foot could
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34476:26"/>paſs them: Our Foot in the mean time followed theirs, through the <hi>Bog,</hi> into a Wood near <hi>Loghearn,</hi> and gave Quarter to none but Officers; which the Enemy perceiving, and having no Courage to fight for their Lives, deſperately took the <hi>Lough,</hi> to the number of 500; and but one Man of them eſcaped drowning, or elſe was Killed coming out. Our Men continued all Night beating the Buſhes for them; and thus ended that days great Service: Whence we may reckon the ſafety of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ireland; God</hi> having given them the greateſt and moſt remarkable Victory over the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that was obtained in this, or any former Age: They were reckoned 6000, and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> not much above 2000; we killed that day, in the Morning and Afternoon, about 3000; took 400 Priſoners; and there were drowned in ſeveral places of <hi>Loghearn,</hi> as was computed, about 500. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> themſelves confeſs there were 3000 of their Men wanting, when thoſe that fled came to <hi>Dublin.</hi> We had in this Action but 20 Men Killed, and about 50 Wounded, whereof many Mortal.</p>
               <p>Lieutenant General <hi>Mac Carty,</hi> after the Fight, when his Men were fled, he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34476:26"/>with about five or ſix Officers, went into a Wood near the place where the Canon were planted; and ſome ſmall time after came out of the Wood with thoſe that were with him, on Horſeback, and Fired his Piſtol at the Party that were guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cannon. Our Men, when they came firſt from the Wood, thought them ſome of their own Party, (ſuppoſing all the Enemy fled) and never queſtioned them till <hi>Mac-Carty</hi> fired his Piſtol; and the 7 or 8 of the Soldiers fired their Muskets at him, ſhot his Horſe dead, and wounded him very ill in ſeveral places, and then to put him out of pain, one of the Soldiers clubbed his Musket to have knocked out his Brains, which one of thoſe that came with him from the Wood perceiving, called to the Soldier to hold his Hand, for it was their General <hi>Mac-Carty;</hi> at the hearing of which, Captain <hi>Cooper</hi> came up, and gave Lieutenant General <hi>Mac-Carty,</hi> and thoſe that were with him, Quarter, and that Night car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him to <hi>Newtown-Butler:</hi> and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ask'd how he came ſo raſhly to haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard his Life, when he might have gone off with his Horſe, when they made their eſcape, profeſt, That he found now the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34476:27"/>Kingdom like to be loſt, his Army being the beſt (for their number) that K. <hi>James</hi> had, unleſs thoſe before <hi>Derry,</hi> who were then much broken; and that he came with a deſign to loſe his Life, and was ſorry that he miſſed of his End, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to out-live that day.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 4. Advice came to <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> that the Siege of <hi>Derry</hi> was raiſed, on <hi>Thurſday</hi> the firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the Morning, a little before day, and that the Army which lay before it, was marched paſt <hi>Omagh.</hi> Upon this Lieutenant <hi>W. Charleton</hi> was ſent, with about a Troop of detatched Horſe, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army on their March to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Charlemont;</hi> who returned on <hi>Monday,</hi> and told us, That he had ſeen the Rear of them paſs by <hi>Caſtle Crowfield,</hi> within Three ſhort Miles of <hi>Dunganon,</hi> and ſo it was in vain to follow them.</p>
               <p>And thus having defeated Lieutenant General <hi>Mac-Carty</hi>'s Party, taken him Priſoner, <hi>Sarsfield</hi> fled, and the Siege of <hi>Derry</hi> being raiſed, their Fears were now at an end, and for ſome time <hi>Inniskilling</hi> was at quiet, from all their Enemies; and the name of <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Men became a Terror to the <hi>Iriſh:</hi> They had nothing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34476:27"/>left to Imploy them, after this, but to take care to Regiment their Men, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Commiſſions Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> gave them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> 7. Mr. <hi>A. Hamilton</hi> was ſent by the Officers at <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> to Major General <hi>Kirk,</hi> to Congratulate with him for his happy Succeſſes, in the Relief of <hi>Derry;</hi> the General receiv'd him very favourably, and ſent him back with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Colonel <hi>Woolſely,</hi> to ſend him 700 Horſe and Dragoons, that he might March the Foot he had towards <hi>Colrain;</hi> and ſo towards Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> (whom he had Advice was at Sea.) The <hi>Innis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing</hi> Horſe marched before the Major General all the way, until his Party joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Duke <hi>Schomberg,</hi> at <hi>Carick-fergus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:34476:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Duke <hi>Schomberg,</hi> with the Army, Embarks at <hi>Highlake,</hi> with Ninety Sail of Ships. Lands at <hi>Bangor.</hi> The Men lye on their Arms all Night. The Caſtle of <hi>Antrim</hi> Taken. The Enemy quits <hi>Belfaſt. Carick-fergus</hi> reſolves to make a reſolute Defence. The Duke in the Trenches. Batteries raiſed, and the Town Bombarded. Hot Firing on both ſides. Officers Killed in the Trenches. The Famous Engineer <hi>Richards</hi> carried out Wounded. The Town offers to Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate, and Surrenders upon Articles, after <hi>20</hi> days Siege. The Army Decamps, marches to <hi>Newry;</hi> on the approach of whom, the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> Burns and quits the Place. The Army Encamps on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ON <hi>Thurſday</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1689. Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> Embark'd at <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lake,</hi> on Board the <hi>Cleveland</hi>-Yatch, about ſix in the Morning; the whole day was employ'd in getting the Forces on Board, and the next day they continued ſtill in the Road, the Wind <hi>South S. Eaſt,</hi> but often veering, the remainder of the Foot
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34476:28"/>Embarqued: <hi>Saturday,</hi> about Three in the Afternoon, the Fleet weigh'd, but came to an Anchor in the ſame Road, lower down. <hi>Sunday</hi> the Fleet continued at Anchor, it being Calm; but on <hi>Monday</hi> about Four in the Afternoon, the Wind being at <hi>S. S. E.</hi> and <hi>S. E.</hi> the <hi>Bonadven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> Captain <hi>Hobſon</hi> Commander, Fir'd a Gun, and put our his light in the main Top-maſt Shrouds, That being the Signal for Sailing. The Fleet conſiſting of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 80 and 90 Sail: The Men of War were, the <hi>Bonadventure, Antelope, James Gally, Princeſs Ann,</hi> &amp;c. (the whole Fleet being under Sail): About ſix a Clock, the <hi>Bonadventure</hi> put out a ſign on the Mizen-Shroud for all the Maſters to come on Board, where they receiv'd Orders to Sail directly for <hi>Carick fergus;</hi> but in caſe of bad Weather, that they could not reach thither, then to Sail for <hi>Longrea</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and if they fell ſhort of that, to <hi>Ramſy-Bay</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> the <hi>13th</hi> at break of day, the Fleet were fairly up with the Mountain of <hi>Dundium,</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ireland:</hi> About Three in the Afternoon (the Wind ſtill being at <hi>South-Eaſt</hi>) they came up the <hi>Lough,</hi> about a League and half from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34476:29"/>
                  <hi>Corick-fergus:</hi> At four the Fleet came to an Anchor in <hi>Bangor-Bay;</hi> immediately the General put out a Jack-flag at the Mizzen-Pick, that being the Signal for Landing the Men: They Encamped in the fields, cloſe to Shore-ſides, and lay on their Arms all tha Night: The next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Rebels in <hi>Carick-fergus</hi> ſet fire to the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Quarters, parts of the Town ſo called, which continued burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that Night and the next day. On <hi>Thurſday</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Fielding,</hi> with a Party of about 250 Men, went out to ſee what poſture the Enemy about <hi>Belfaſt</hi> were in, and returned that Evening. <hi>Thurſday</hi> the <hi>16th</hi> a Party of Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Fire-locks, Commanded by Lieut. Colonel <hi>Caulfield,</hi> marched on through <hi>Belfaſt</hi> (where Colonel <hi>Wharton</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had poſted themſelves) and poſſeſt himſelf of the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> the Rebels marching out the Night before in great confuſion, towards <hi>Toom,</hi> where a ſmall Fort had been thrown up formerly to ſecure a paſs that is there. <hi>Tueſday</hi> the <hi>20th</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Caulfield,</hi> with 250 of his Party, returned to the Army, 50 remaining to ſecure the Town and Caſtle, Commanded by Captain <hi>Ormſby,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:34476:29"/>and Lieutenant <hi>Wallis.</hi> On <hi>Thurſday,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Regiments of Foot Encamped almoſt round the Town of <hi>Carick fergus;</hi> that day was ſpent in Planting the Canon and Mortars, and in making ſome ſmall Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: The Town deſired a Parly, which, though granted, came to nothing, They requiring time to ſend to the late King, for leave to Surrender; this held for a ſhort while, after which the Cannons and Bombs were play'd very ſmartly againſt the Lord <hi>Dunegal</hi>'s Houſe (out of which they had Planted Two Guns, that did us ſome little damage) and againſt the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> on the right of the Caſtle, our Soldiers mounted the Trenches with great Bravery, and having made their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches near the Town, fired their ſmall Shot very thick, nor were the Enemy Idle, though we loſt very few Men, only a Captain Killed, and Lieutenant <hi>Adams</hi> Wounded in the Thigh (which proved Mortal,) our Army ſtill nearer approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Playing their Cannon, and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Bombs and Carcaſſes in great numbers into the Town and Caſtle. <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the 22. about 50 Sail of Ships came up the <hi>Lough,</hi> who had brought over four Regiments of Foot, and one of Horſe:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34476:30"/>The day and night was ſpent in ſmart firing on both ſides, with the loſs of ſome few Officers and private Soldiers. <hi>Friday</hi> the 23. about Three a clock, the Town again deſired a Parley, and would Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render. The Duke allowing them to march out without ſtriping, and their hands in their Pockets, without being Plundred, which the Duke refuſed, and would agree to no leſs than the making them all Priſoners of War, during their Majeſties Pleaſure: The time of the Parley, Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> went through the Trenches and viewed them, as alſo the Walls of the Caſtle. The Parley being over, the Duke gave Orders to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineers and Gunners to go on as Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly as poſſible they could; tho' before, the Duke had ordered them to ſpare the Caſtle: Our Batteries being only one on the <hi>Windmil-Hill;</hi> with Mortars, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother againſt the <hi>North-Gate</hi> of four Guns; the Duke ordered a very large Mortar to be planted on a new Battery, cloſe under the Walls, near the Lord <hi>Dunegal</hi>'s Houſe, with a ſmall Field-piece, which did great Execution; our Canon, Mortars, and ſmall Shot, playing very furiouſly all the Night.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:34476:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> the 24. At break of day the Town was all over covered with Duſt and Smoak, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and about Eight, ſome Houſes were flaming. Engineer <hi>Richards</hi> who came from <hi>Derry,</hi> was carried to <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> being Wounded in three ſeveral places, as he was in the Trenches. At Two a Clock this day came one Mr. <hi>Spring</hi> to the Duke, who made his eſcape over the Walls, and gave an account, That all the Soldiers lay continually on the Walls; ſo that the Bombs only af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted the <hi>Protestants</hi> in the Town: And that <hi>O Mac-Carty Moor,</hi> and <hi>Owen Mac-Carty</hi> were the only Two that obſtructed the Surrendring of the Town. <hi>Sunday</hi> and <hi>Munday</hi> there was ſmart Firing on both ſides, and ſome Breaches made in the Walls. On <hi>Tueſday,</hi> being the 27. a White Flag was hung out. After the Ships, no leſs than our Army, had done them very great damage, they being moved in a Line againſt the Caſtle, and they Surrendred on condition to have their liberty to march to the next Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. The next day the Army marched to <hi>Belfast,</hi> leaving Sir <hi>H. Ingolsby</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Garriſon there.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:34476:31"/>
               <p>On <hi>Monday Sept.</hi> 2. The whole Army march'd Two Miles beyond <hi>Liſnegarvy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 3. They Encamped near the Town of <hi>Dramore;</hi> and the ſame Night the Train of Artillery came up and ioyned the Army.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> we Encamped on the ſide of a Hill, near the Town of <hi>Lough-brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in Two Lines, as at firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 5. The Army Encamped about a Mile ſhort of the <hi>Newry:</hi> The night before, the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> left the Town, after having Burnt all but a few Houſes. The next day the Army paſſed through the Town, and continued their March towards <hi>Dundalk.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:34476:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Duke <hi>Sconberg,</hi> on the Burning of the <hi>Newry,</hi> ſends a Trumpet to the Duke of <hi>Berwick.</hi> The Enemy quit <hi>Dundalk</hi> without Burning it. Our Army Encamp on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk.</hi> The Enemy about <hi>Ardee.</hi> Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> Defeats <hi>5000 Iriſh</hi> near <hi>Slego,</hi> Kills <hi>700,</hi> and takes <hi>300</hi> Priſoners, with their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander. A Conſpiracy of <hi>French Papiſts</hi> diſcovered in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Camp. A Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Four others Hanged. <hi>150</hi> more ſent Priſoners to <hi>England.</hi> Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> with a Party of <hi>Inniskilling</hi>-Men, takes the Caſtle of <hi>Dramnaſna</hi> &amp; <hi>James-Town.</hi> Great Mortality in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Camp, of which <hi>15000</hi> Die. Duke <hi>Schomberg's</hi> Proclamation of Proviſions. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> March into Winter Quarters. <hi>James-Town</hi> quitted. The Fight at <hi>Slego,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Colonel <hi>Lloyd,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Officer, and <hi>Sarsfield.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army Decamp, and go into Winter Quarters. The Actions of the <hi>Newry,</hi> between a Party of Colonel <hi>Ingolsby</hi>'s, and <hi>1700 Iriſh.</hi> Colonel <hi>Cambon</hi>'s Action at <hi>Charlemont.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Enemy having Burnt the greater part of the Town of <hi>Newry,</hi> before
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34476:32"/>they quitted it, the General ſent a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter (<hi>Sept.</hi> 6.) to the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> who Commanded there, to let him know, <hi>That if they went on to Burn in this Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous manner, he would not give any Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> which Meſſage had this Effect, That the <hi>Iriſh</hi> abandoned <hi>Dundalk</hi> without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any harm to the Town, leaving be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind a great deal of Proviſions, which their fear and haſt would not ſuffer them to carry away. The Army continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Dundalk</hi> and the <hi>Newry</hi> for ſeveral days, waiting the coming of their Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, which coming up on the 16 Inſtant, and on the 17 and 18 we Encamped very advantagiouſly on the Plains about <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalk;</hi> at the ſame time, the Enemy lay Intrench'd at <hi>Ardee,</hi> about 46000 Strong. After we were Encamped, our Army al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every day encreaſed with new For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, either from <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> for ſeveral Weeks.</p>
               <p>On the 25. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces, Quartered in and about <hi>Connaught,</hi> came with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to ſurpriſe the Town of <hi>Slego,</hi> to the number of 5000 Horſe and Foot, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Colonel <hi>O Kelly:</hi> Of which Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> having timely Intelligence, muſtered up his <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Forces, making
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34476:32"/>in all about 1000 Horſe, Foot and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, with whom he was reſolved to Fight the Enemy; and having Poſted his Horſe very advantagiouſly, on a riſing Ground, and lined the Hedges with his Foot, in a Lane near the Town of <hi>Boyle,</hi> through which they were to Paſs: The Enemy were no ſooner come up, but our Men charged them with all the Vigour and Courage imaginable, and after a ſhort time put them to Flight, which Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> perceiving, took a circumference with his Horſe and Dragoons, and got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Boyle</hi> (through which the Enemy were to paſs) before them, where meeting with the Enemy, charged them in the Front with his Horſe, whil'ſt the Foot fell upon the Rear, that they killed 700 on the ſpot, and took 300 Priſoners, among which were Colonel <hi>O Kelly,</hi> their Commander, and 40 other Officers, a great number of Arms, 8000 Head of Cattle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The News of this great Victory coming to His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg,</hi> He or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Cannon to be Fired in all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Quarters.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>28th</hi> A Treacherous Conſpiracy was diſcovered in our Camp, which was carried on by ſome <hi>French Papiſts:</hi> The
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34476:33"/>particulars of which was as followeth:</p>
               <p>A Captain, in one of the <hi>French</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, being inform'd by one of his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, That four other Soldiers, and a Drummer, who were <hi>Papiſts,</hi> deſigned to go over to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, he cauſed them to be ſeized, and found Letters about one of them to Monſieur <hi>D' Avaux,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined, declared he had the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from one <hi>Du Pleſſy,</hi> likewiſe a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> who now ſerved as a private Soldier, in one of the <hi>French</hi> Regiments, tho' he had been formerly a Captain of Horſe in <hi>France,</hi> from whence he was forced to retire, on the Account of a Murther he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted there. <hi>Du Pleſſy</hi> being ſeized, upon his Examination confeſſed, That he had written to the late King, and to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>D' Avaux,</hi> giving them an account, that there were divers <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Regiments, and promiſing to bring them over to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Camp, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he might have the Command of them, and his Pardon in <hi>France.</hi> He, and his ſive Accomplices were brought to a Tryal, where Sentence of Death paſſed upon them, and they were Executed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. After which, the Three <hi>French</hi> Colone's made ſtrict enquiry what <hi>Papiſts</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:34476:33"/>there were in their Regiments, and found about 150. who, by Order of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, were ſecured, and ſent Priſoners to <hi>Carlingford,</hi> and afterwards to <hi>England.</hi> Moſt of theſe had deſerted the <hi>French</hi> Service this Summer, and paſſing to <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and thence to <hi>England,</hi> upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that Three <hi>French</hi> Regiments were levying here, had Liſted themſelves in the ſame; the Officers raiſing their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in ſo much haſt, that they had not time to examine them very ſtrictly.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>1ſt</hi> of <hi>October</hi> Colonel <hi>Thomas Lloyd</hi> being informed, That the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had put a Garriſon of about 80 Men into <hi>James-Town,</hi> which is no inconſiderable Paſs upon the River <hi>Shannon,</hi> he marched thither with the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Men under his Command: Upon our approach they Fired very briskly upon us, though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing us any other damage, than that one Man was Shot in his Leg, and a Horſe Killed; Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> having lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Dragoons as near the Town, as he could conveniently do, Marched with the Horſe towards a Paſs upon the ſame Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, called <hi>Drumnaſna,</hi> Colonel <hi>Mac Donel</hi>'s Houſe, which was immediately Surrendred to him, where he found Two
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34476:34"/>great Pantoons, which would have faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litated his going over the Water, to have Surrounded the Town. But about Twelve at Night, ſome <hi>Proteſtants</hi> came and gave him notice, That the Rebels had aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the place; whereupon he poſſeſſed himſelf of it, and afterwards returned with a conſiderable Booty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>October</hi> 10. Several <hi>Iriſh</hi> Deſerters came into our Camp, who gave us an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, That the late King <hi>James</hi> had loſt above Fifteen Thouſand of his Army ſince they had been Encamped about <hi>Ardee,</hi> that a very malignant <hi>Fever</hi> did rage in their Camp, with ſeveral other Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: About this time, a great deal of Rain fell for ſeveral days together, which occaſioned ſuch great quantities of ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water, that great numbers, both of Officers and Soldiers, dyed in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Camp, but not near ſo many as dyed in the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> being Informed, That notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there was ſo great a Plenty in our Camp, of almoſt all ſorts of Proviſions, yet the Sutlers, and other Country People that attended the Camp, extorted extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Rates from the Soldiers in the Army; He cauſed a Proclamation to be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34476:34"/>Publiſhed, limiting the Prizes of all ſorts of Proviſions to a certain moderate Rate.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>1ſt</hi> of <hi>November</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army decamped, and March d into Winter-Quarters, having lain Encamped about <hi>Ardee,</hi> ever ſince the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> without attempting to force our Camp, notwithſtanding they were near double the number.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>November</hi> 4. Advice came to <hi>James-Town,</hi> That Colonel <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tached Body of Five Thouſand choice Men out of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, and joyned with Two Thouſand of the <hi>Connaught</hi> Forces, was coming to Attack that place; on which the Garriſon, not finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves able to engage with ſo great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were, retreated thence to <hi>Sligoe;</hi> Killing, in their Retreat, 45 of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> with the loſs of Nine of their own Party: <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, the next day, came before the Town of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> whereupon Colonel <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> with the Horſe under his Command (appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending <hi>Sarsfield</hi>'s Party to be too ſtrong for them) retreated to <hi>Belliſhannon,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing the Foot alſo to quit the Town: But one Monſieur <hi>De St. Sauvem,</hi> who Commanded about Two Hundred Foot,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34476:35"/>moſt Granadeers, and Colonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> with the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Foot, bravely ſtood to it, reſolving to Fight the Enemy; and upon their approaching the Town, the <hi>French</hi> Captain, with his Men, went and took a Paſs not far from the Town, which he maintained againſt all <hi>Sarsfield</hi>'s force, till all their Ammunition was ſpent; the Monſieur himſelf, an excellent Markſman, often firing in the Head of them; after which, he and his Men Retreated to the Town, with no great loſs, and defended themſelves with their Bionets in their Muſquets, till they took Poſſeſſion of the Two Forts beyond the Town. The <hi>French</hi> Captain and his Party poſſeſſing the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Fort; and <hi>Lloyd,</hi> with the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Men, went to the upper Fort; from whence <hi>Lloyd</hi> that Night went towards <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> falling on the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in a Paſs which he was to go over, and Killing Two hundred, loſing but Twenty five himſelf: The <hi>French,</hi> in their Retreat, carried Fire and Proviſions into the Fort, wherein they found three Barrels of Powder, with which they defended themſelves bravely for three days; and on the Third, at Night, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> lying ſecure in the Town, they Sallied from the Fort, on the <hi>Iriſh,</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34476:35"/>killed about One hundred and Twenty, and drove the reſt out of the Town; which account being brought to Duke <hi>Schonberg,</hi> he diſpatched away all the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Horſe and Dragoons, with Two Regiments of Foot; but before they could arrive, the Town was preſſed on by <hi>Sarsfield</hi>'s whole Army, with ſo great Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, that they were forced to quit it in the Night, and made an handſome Retreat to <hi>Inniskilling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Novemb.</hi> 8. Our Army began to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp, Ten Regiments marched away laſt Night, and the reſt followed this day; and His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg</hi> marched away to <hi>Liſnegarvy,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Lisburne.</hi> Our Army lay En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped from the <hi>16th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> to the <hi>18th</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk;</hi> during which time, little of Action happened between the Two Armies, but Skirmiſhes with the Out-Scouts, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned chiefly by our want of Horſe, and the Cowardiſe of the late King <hi>James</hi> and his Army, that they durſt not make any attempt on our Camp, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Army conſiſted of near double our number.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>November</hi> a Detached
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34476:36"/>Party of ſelect <hi>Iriſh</hi> came about break of day to <hi>Newry-Bridge,</hi> before they were perceived: The Two Centinels that were placed there, having twice diſcharged their Muskets, were killed on the Spot, and the Enemy got into the Town; but, after an hours diſpute, were beaten out again, by a ſmall Party of Colonel <hi>Ingols<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi>'s Regiment; in this occaſion we loſt 2 Capt 6 or 7 private Soldiers, and a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant and an Enſign were Wounded. About Ten a Clock of the ſame day the <hi>Iriſh</hi> return'd, and got over the Bridge a a ſecond time; but our Men receiv'd them ſo warmly, that they ſoon return'd in great confuſion, leaving Twelve of their Company Slain on the Bridge, with Two or Three Officers, whom they drag'd away with them; and in this laſt Action we had only Two Men Wounded: The Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Bravery of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred extreamly remarkable, by the vaſt inequality of theſe Two Parties; the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being Seventeen Hundred Strong, Horſe, Foot, and Dragoons.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>26th</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> Colonel <hi>Cambon</hi> going to take a view of the Caſtle and Garriſon of <hi>Charlemont,</hi> took with him a ſmall Party, conſiſting of Sixty of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34476:36"/>Colonel <hi>Leviſton</hi>'s Regiment of Dragoons, who coming within Two Miles of the Place were diſcovered by the Enemies advanced Sentinels; the Garriſon took the Alarm, and when our Men came to the Hill, from whence they might view the place, they found all the Hedges and Buſhes lined; whereupon the Dragoons alighted, and beat the Rebels from their Poſt; how many were Killed or Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as they ran over the Bog was not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly known, but the Dragoons had a fair Mark at 300 of them, as they run to the Town. Our Men found Eight or Nine Dead on the place, among the Hedges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:34476:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Defeated at the <hi>Newry,</hi> by Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadeer <hi>Steward, 30</hi> Killed, and <hi>7</hi> Taken Priſoners. Colonel <hi>Wolſely</hi> takes <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbet.</hi> Lady <hi>Newcomens</hi> Houſe Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred. Duke <hi>Schonberg</hi> views <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont,</hi> and takes Booty under the Walls. Colonel <hi>Berry,</hi> and <hi>St. John</hi> takes great Plunder. Duke <hi>Sconberg</hi>'s Proclamation againſt Cuaſing and Swearing. Duke <hi>Sconberg</hi> with a Party goes to <hi>Dundalk.</hi> Colonel <hi>Woolſely</hi> defeats the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> at <hi>Cavan,</hi> kills <hi>300,</hi> takes great number of Officers Priſoners, and <hi>200</hi> Common Soldiers. Brigadeer <hi>Nugent</hi> Mortally Wounded. Four Thouſand pound in Braſs-Money taken from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels. Sir <hi>John Laneer</hi> takes <hi>Bedloe</hi>-Caſtle. Prince of <hi>Wirtenburgh</hi> and the <hi>Danes,</hi> Land at <hi>Belfaſt.</hi> The Famous Action of Monſieur <hi>Callimate</hi> at <hi>Charlemont. 5000 French</hi> Land at <hi>Kinſale.</hi> Colonel <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Tryal at <hi>Lisburn,</hi> for the Eſcape of General <hi>Mac-Carty.</hi> The Famous Action of Sir <hi>Cloudſly Shovel</hi> at <hi>Dublin</hi>-Bay.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOv.</hi> 29. Brigadeer General <hi>Steward</hi> receiving Intelligence by ſome <hi>Iriſh</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:34476:37"/>Deſerters, That the Rebels Quartered in <hi>Dundalk,</hi> had formed a Deſign, to ſurpriſe the Town and Paſs of the <hi>Newry,</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi>'s Regiment Quartered there. He immediately drew out what Horſe and Foot the little time would permit, which exceeded not in all above Two Hundred and Fifty Men, and went in Perſon at the Head of them, and drew them up on a very advantagious Ground near the Paſs, juſt as the Enemy came up; and our Party Attackt them ſo vigorouſly, that they ſoon put the Enemy to the Rout, Killing 30 on the Spot, and taking Seventeen Priſoners, among which were Five Officers: He likewiſe took ſome hundred Head of Cattle, and ſmall Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons. And had our Party been larger, the General was reſolved to have march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Dundalk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 4. Colonel <hi>Wolſely</hi> marched out with a ſmall Party of the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Forces in the Night to <hi>Belturbet,</hi> and taking the Garriſon at a ſurpriſe, upon the firſt Summons they yielded, to be conducted to the next Garriſon. About the ſame time, a conſiderable Party of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces had Attacked the Houſe of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Newcomen,</hi> in the County of <hi>Longford,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:34476:38"/>which ſhe defended very Bravely, with the aſſiſtance of Two hundred of her <hi>Britiſh</hi> Tenants, that ſhe had got into her Houſe; neither could they take it for ſome time, tho' they had made ſeveral vigorous At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks upon it, (it being above 20 Miles from any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garriſon) until they had brought ſome of their Field-Pieces and Bombs againſt it; yet ſuch was the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry and Reſolution of the Lady, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe maintained the Place, even after the arrival of theſe Warlike Engines, that ſhe forced the Enemy to give very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious and honourable Terms; namely, That her Ladyſhip and Domeſtick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhould continue in the Houſe as formerly, the Garriſon having free liberty to March with their Arms, Bag and Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to <hi>Liſnegarvy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>December</hi> His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg</hi> went, with a ſmall Party, to view the ſituation of <hi>Charlemont,</hi> and took from under the Walls of the place, fifty Horſes, forty Cows, and about the like number of Sheep, without the leaſt oppoſition from the Rebels in Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, except the firing of the Canon, which did us no harm. Our Forces at this time began to be in a very good condition;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34476:38"/>and moſt of the Soldiers that were Sick in the Hoſpital, began now to be very well recovered, and gone to their Quarters, but we had it confirmed among us, from all hands, that there ſtill continued a great Mortality among the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>1ſt</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> Lieut. Colonel <hi>Berry</hi> went out with a detached Party from <hi>Clowniſh,</hi> and after having ranged for ſome time, without being able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover any Enemy, he returned with the Plunder of Fifteen Hundred Cows, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Sheep and Garrons, or ſmall Horſes; and ſome time after, another Party, which Colonel <hi>Saint John</hi>'s ſent out from <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh,</hi> brought back Sixty Horſes, and an Hundred and fifty Sheep.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>January</hi> 8. About this time Parties went out from ſeveral of our Garriſons, and made Excurſions into the Enemies Quarters, and brought away ſeveral Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Head of black Cattle, Sheep, and ſmall Horſes or Garrons.</p>
               <p>Complaint being made to His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg</hi> at <hi>Lisburne,</hi> of ſome
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34476:39"/>Irregularities of our Army, particularly, the too frequent uſe of Curſing and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; His Grace immediately ordered the following Proclamation to be Publiſhed, Entituled,</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="proclamation">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Proclamation by <hi>Frederick,</hi> Duke of <hi>Schonberg,</hi> Lord General of all Their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Forces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHereas the Horrid and Deteſtable Crimes of Profane Curſing, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and taking Gods Holy Name in vain, being Sins of much Guilt and little Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, have, by all Nations and People, and that in all Ages, been puniſhed with ſharp and ſevere Penalties, as great and grievous Sins: And we, to our great Grief and Trouble, taking notice of the too ſrequent practice of theſe Sins, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral under Our Command; and that ſome have arrived to that height of Impiety, that they are heard more irequently to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God to Damn them, than to Save them; and this notwithſtanding the heavy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34476:39"/>and dreadful Iudgments of God upon us, at this very time, for theſe and our other Sins, and notwithſtanding the Penalties enjoyned by Their Majeſties Articles of War on theſe Offenders; And we juſtly fearing that Their Majeſties Army may be more prejudiced by theſe Sins, than ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged by the Conduct and Courage of thoſe Guilty of them, do think fit, ſtrictly to Charge and Command all Officers and Soldiers under Our Command That they, and every of them, from hence-forward do forbear all vain Curſing, Swearing, and taking God's Holy Name in vain, under the Penalties enjoyned by the aforeſaid Articles, and Our further Diſpleaſure: And that all Officers take particular care to put the ſaid Articles of War in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on all under their reſpective Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, guilty of the ſaid Offences, as they will anſwer the contrary at their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Peril.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given at Our Head Quarters at <hi>Lisburn,</hi> 
                           <date>the 18th of <hi>January,</hi> 1689. in the Firſt Year of Their Majeſties Reign.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Signed <hi>SCHONBERG.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:34476:40"/>
               <p>On the <hi>25th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg</hi> ſet out from <hi>Lisburn,</hi> to viſit our Forces in the Frontier Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and gave the neceſſary Orders, and returned again on the <hi>30th.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On <hi>Feb.</hi> 6. A great number of Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allers arrived at <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> and brought us an account, that the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Forces were on their March, in order to their being Embarked for this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 12. His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> our General, having advice brought him to <hi>Lisburn,</hi> That the Enemy were in motion about <hi>Dundalk,</hi> he drew ſome Troops together, and Marched himſelf with them to <hi>Dramore;</hi> but Sir <hi>John Lanier</hi> and Colonel <hi>La Melioner,</hi> who were ſent before with a Party, and went as far as <hi>Carlingford,</hi> returned with an account that there were only Three Regiments at <hi>Dundalk,</hi> neither that Garriſon nor <hi>Drog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedagh</hi> having receiv'd any reinforcements, the Troops were countermanded, except a Detachment of 500 Horſe and Dragoons, and as many Foot, which was ſent under the Command of Sir <hi>John Lanier,</hi> towards
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34476:40"/>
                  <hi>Dundalk,</hi> who had afterwards divers ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Skirmiſhes with the Enemy.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>13th</hi> His Grace returned to <hi>Lisburne,</hi> where he receiv'd the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Account, by Letters from Colonel <hi>Wolſely,</hi> Dated at <hi>Belturbet,</hi> the <hi>12th,</hi> as followeth:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>I ſend your Grace this Expreſs, to give you an account of the Fight we had Ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday with the Enemy at <hi>Cavan:</hi> On <hi>Monday,</hi> at Four in the Afternoon, I marched from <hi>Belturbet</hi> with a Detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 700 Foot, and 300 Horſe and Dragoons: We paſſed the River at 12 at Night, Two Miles above <hi>Callihays,</hi> where were Two of the Enemies Scouts; The Signal of our Motion was given, by Firing ſeveral Muſquets down the River, and making a great Fire upon a high Hill. I had carried my Men all over about one a Clock, and intended to have been at <hi>Cavan</hi> about an hour before day, but the Ways were ſo bad, and defiles ſo many, that we got not thither till half an hour after day-break, where we found the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> (which I did not
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34476:41"/>expect) who arrived there the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with 2500 Men, which, with the Garriſon, made a Body of 4000 Men, all drawn up in good order before the Town, and near the Fort; ſo ſoon as I had diſpoſed of my Men as the Ground would give me leave, I charged them, and after an hours diſpute, we beat them out of the Field. The Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> had his Horſe ſhot. Colonel <hi>O Rely,</hi> Governor of <hi>Cavan,</hi> killed on the place, with two Lieutenant Colonels, the one a <hi>French-man,</hi> the other an <hi>Iriſh-man,</hi> whoſe Name was <hi>Goughagan,</hi> a Man in great Eſteem with them; but moſt of our Men fell preſently upon the Plunder, both in the Field and in the Town, ſo that we were in the greateſt confuſion imaginable, which the Enemy ſeeing from the Fort, made a very ſtrong Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon us, and came on ſo briskly that I thought all had been loſt: I went with all the ſpeed I could to a place, where I had poſted ſome Detatchments of Foot at the beginning of the Fight, who had not been engaged at all, and I found them all there, being about 250; with theſe, and about 80 Horſe and Dragoons,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34476:41"/>I oppoſed the Enemy, who I judged to be about 1500: At the ſame time, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it impoſſible to get our Men out of the Town, I ſent a Party of Horſe with Orders to Burn it, which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately done, and ſo the Soldiers were forced to quit it, and having joyned thoſe that were Fighting, we drove the Enemy like Sheep into the Fort, which being a ſtrong Place, and full of Men, and our Men being extreamly fatiegued, I did not think fit to Attack it. It was a very unfortunate force, which the Soldiers, falling to Plunder, put upon me, to Burn the Town, for there was in it as much Proviſion as would have ſerved this Garriſon ſix Months: All the Houſes were full of Bread, Meal, and Wheat, and a vaſt quantity of Oats and Beans.</p>
                  <p>The Priſoners give me this Account; That the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> was to Command, at <hi>Cavan,</hi> a Body of Ten Thouſand Men, which were to be made up by Detachments out of the whole Army: The firſt place he was to At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack was this, which was to have been done this day, and theſe were the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34476:42"/>your Grace had ſo frequent Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of; but I ſuppoſe the Neck of this Deſign is broke, we having deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all their Proviſions both for Men and Horſe; and what I believe is as great a loſs to them, we have blown up all their Ammunition which was lodged in the Town: So ſoon as my Men have refreſhed themſelves, I will have another Bout with them for the Fort, which I believe they will quit of themſelves, for they have no Proviſions or cover for their Men, now the Town is deſtroyed. We have loſt about Twenty Men; my Major <hi>Traherne,</hi> Captain <hi>Armſtrong,</hi> and Captain <hi>Mayo,</hi> with Captain <hi>La Maugere,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Officer, were killed, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Blood</hi> an Ingineer ſhot in the ſide: Of the Enemy, Three Hundred were killed; and four Captains, five Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, two Enſigns, and a Quarter-Maſter, with Two Hundred Men taken Priſoners. Our Men ſhewed in this (as in former occaſions) a very great forwardneſs to Engage the Enemy, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the inequality of their Number, and gave new prooſs of their
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34476:42"/>Courage and Bravery; and particularly Major General <hi>Kirk</hi>'s Men.</p>
                  <p>The Eight <hi>French</hi> Officers your Grace ſent hither, likewiſe behaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very well.</p>
               </q>
               <p>This day, being <hi>February</hi> the <hi>16th,</hi> His Grace received another Expreſs from Colonel <hi>Wolſely,</hi> with the following Account, Written at <hi>Belturbet</hi> the <hi>14th</hi> Inſtant.</p>
               <q>Since I Writ my laſt, a Gentleman is come in here from the County of <hi>Weſtmeath,</hi> who tells me, he ſaw, after the Fight at <hi>Cavan,</hi> great numbers of Soldiers, all without Arms, having thrown them away in their flight; ſo that the Road and Ditches were filled with them: That he ſaw likewiſe a great many Wounded Men, among whom were ſeveral Officers: That Brigadeer General <hi>Nugent</hi> was Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally Wounded: And that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> own the loſs of Three Hundred Men, and of Fourteen Commiſſion Officers killed upon the Place. We have taken from the Enemy 4000 pound in Braſs Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</q>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:34476:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>February</hi> 17. Twelve Officers, <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that were Taken at the Battle at <hi>Cavan,</hi> were brought Priſoners to the Caſtle of <hi>Carick-fergus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>February</hi> 20. Sir <hi>John Lanier,</hi> with his Party at the <hi>Newry,</hi> marched from thence to <hi>Dundalk;</hi> and paſſing by <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loe</hi>-Caſtle, in which there was an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, with Thirty Four Men, Colonel <hi>Leviſon</hi>'s Dragoons immediately Stormed it, Killed Ten of the Rebels, and took the reſt Priſoners, and Burnt the Caſtle, in which there was a great deal of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions: Then they advanced to the back of the Town of <hi>Dundalk;</hi> Briga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadeer <hi>Steward</hi> marching at the ſame time with the Foot, to the other ſide of the Town, and Burnt about Twenty Houſes; the Garriſon keeping cloſe with their Intrenchments: After which they returned to <hi>Newry,</hi> with a Booty of a Thouſand Cows, and Two Hundred Garoons, having had a <hi>French</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Killed, and five Dragoons Wounded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 6. Four Hundred <hi>Danes</hi> Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> and the next day, the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34476:43"/>Prince of <hi>Wirtenburgh,</hi> their General, Landed with many more: On which, His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg,</hi> went from <hi>Lisburne</hi> to take a View of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Forces, and gave Orders for their ſeveral Quarters in particular Towns.</p>
               <p>The Regiment of <hi>Callimote</hi> being poſted this Winter along the River cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Black-Water,</hi> and near <hi>Lough-Neagh;</hi> they greatly ſtreightned the Garriſon of <hi>Charlemont,</hi> on that ſide, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred their having any Correſpondence with the County of <hi>Tyrone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the <hi>8th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> Colonel <hi>La Callimote</hi> poſſeſſed himſelf of a ſmall Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage within a Mile of <hi>Charlemont.</hi> The Enemy, upon notice of it, came out with 300 Men to Attack us; but though we had not had time to Intrench our ſelves, yet we repulſed them with the loſs of Three Men on their ſide, and one woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on ours. We were employed the next day, and the following, in caſting up ſome little Works, and in obſerving the Avenues of the Place, and the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Out-Poſts on both ſides the River,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34476:44"/>which we obliged them to abandon, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them every Night new Alarms.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>12th</hi> Inſtant, about Nine at Night, Colonel <hi>Callimote</hi> marched with a Party of his Regiment, and a ſmall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment of Colonel <hi>Saint John</hi>'s, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all about Eighty Soldiers and Twenty Officers, whom he cauſed to Embark at a place called <hi>Dery-Gally,</hi> in Three large Boats. Being come within half a Mile of <hi>Charlemont</hi> he Landed his Men, and leaving a Guard with the Boats, marched to the Town, and though they were diſcovered at a good diſtance, by the light of the Moon, yet they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Ditch, and made themſelves Maſters of the Main-Guard. Our Men divided themſelves into Two Parties, the one marched towards the Gate of the Caſtle, to hinder the Rebels from Sallying out, and the other Attackt a Redoubt, lately Built within Thirty Paces of the Counterſcarp to cover their Bridge, which might contain Thirty Men, and had now in it fifteen with a Serjeant, and after ſome little Reſiſtance, entred the ſame, killing Six, and taking the reſt Priſoners.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34476:44"/>Monſieur <hi>de la Borde,</hi> Major to <hi>La Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote,</hi> with Thirty Men, took another Redoubt, and we Plundered and Burnt the Houſes, as far as the Gate of <hi>Armagh,</hi> which the Enemy had abandoned. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, the day coming on, Collonel <hi>Callimote</hi> retired with his Party, with Drums Beating, and Colours Flying, by the Cauſey that leads to <hi>Black-Water</hi> Town. The whole Action was carried on with a great deal of Vigour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct: The Rebels loſt above Fifty Men, killed and taken Priſoners: On our ſide, Major <hi>La Borde</hi> was Killed, with a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage Shot, from the laſt Cannon that was Fired; and Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Belcaſſel,</hi> and Captain <hi>Le Rapin</hi> were Wounded; the firſt in the Head, and the other in the Thigh; and beſides theſe, we had but one Man Killed and Five or Six Wounded. There were then about 450 Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 14th. Five thouſand French Foot Landed at the Port of <hi>Kin-ſale,</hi> with two Generals, the Count <hi>de Lauzun,</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>de Lery;</hi> in Exchange for theſe, the late King <hi>James</hi> ſent his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lewis,</hi> ſome time after, Five Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34476:45"/>
                  <hi>Iriſh,</hi> under the Command of Gen. <hi>Mac-Carty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 15. Colonel <hi>Guſtavus Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> was brought to his Tryal, for the Eſcape of Major General <hi>Mac Carty</hi> from <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> he being Governour of the Town, when the General Eſcaped in the beginning of <hi>January</hi> laſt. The Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel had often urged for a Tryal, but was delayed above Two months, partly for want of Field-Officers, who were the only Perſons that could try him, they being Commanded to their Poſts upon the Alarms we had from <hi>Cavan,</hi> and <hi>Dundalk.</hi> The Court being ſate, Major General <hi>Lanier</hi> Preſident, the Judge Advocate, Sir <hi>John Topham,</hi> laid the Charge againſt him, which having fully done, the Court demanded of the Collonel what he had to offer for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: Upon this the Collonel produced a Letter from his Superior Officer, wherein he commanded him to take <hi>Moncaſhells</hi> Parol for his Behaviour. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this the Court ſaid, he need ſay no more, for the Letter he produced ſpoke enough to ſhow his Innocency.</p>
               <p>The Preſident acquainted the Duke of <hi>Schonberg</hi> with it, who ſent for Moll
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34476:45"/>
                  <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and told him, <hi>He was ſorry for what trouble was given him, but that what was done, was to ſatisfie others more than himſelf, of his Innocency.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 23th. At Night Collonel <hi>Wolſeley</hi> ſent a Party of 200 Men, to fetch in ſome Cattle, for the uſe of his Garriſon at <hi>Belturbet;</hi> who leaving <hi>Cavan</hi> on the right Hand, went Three Miles beyond it, and brought away 1000 Head of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; but as they were returning back by the River, by which they came, they found 400 of the Enemy drawn up in Battalia to hinder their Paſſage, but our Men having put themſelves in a Poſture, Attack'd them with that Courage and Reſolution, that they ſoon put them to the Rout, Killed Forty, and took Eight Priſoners, and Purſued the reſt to the very Gates of <hi>Belinicargate;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 6th. Collonel <hi>Wolſely</hi> this Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Marched from <hi>Belturbet,</hi> with 700 Men, drawn out of the Regiments of <hi>Kirk, Earle Gravan,</hi> and the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Troops; and having ordered half of them to make an Incurſion towards <hi>Finag,</hi> under the command of Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Collonel <hi>Tretchtoune,</hi> he advanced with the reſt to Attack the Caſtle of <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhandra,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:34476:46"/>(Situated about Seven Miles from <hi>Belturbet,</hi> the like diſtance from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van,</hi> and Nine from <hi>Finag</hi>) where he arived the <hi>7th.</hi> about break of Day, and by the help of ſome Hedges and Ditches, brought all his Men within Musket-ſhot of the Caſtle, and fixed a Miner to the Wall: The Mine was fixed, and ready to Play by Ten the next Morning, when Collonel <hi>Wolſely</hi> ſent to Summon the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; who thereupon ſent out an Officer to Treat, and about two Hours after, the Conditions were agreed upon, which were, that the Garriſon ſhould March out with their Arms and Baggage: And accordingly the Caſtle-Gate was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up about Noon, and the Gariſon, Commanded by one Captain <hi>Darchey,</hi> Marched out an Hour after, being 160 Detached Men, out of ſeveral Regiments, and were Guarded to <hi>Cavan:</hi> In this Action, we loſt Three Men, and had Five wounded; and 100 Men were put into the Caſtle, which is a Poſt of very good conſideration to us, it opening a free paſſage into <hi>Connaught,</hi> and to all that part of <hi>Leinſter,</hi> that lyes on the <hi>Shannon.</hi> After this, Collonel <hi>Wolſely</hi> returned to <hi>Belturbet;</hi> whither the General ſent a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34476:46"/>of <hi>Danes</hi> to reinforce him, with Orders to enter upon new Action.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>8th.</hi> Collonel <hi>Cutts,</hi> and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Babingtons</hi> Regiments, with the laſt Regiment of <hi>Daniſh</hi> Horſe, and Recruits for the other Regiments arrived at <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the <hi>10th.</hi> Collonel <hi>Tiffin,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Belliſhannon,</hi> ſent out a Party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of 200 Firelocks of his own Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and 20 Dragoons, Commanded by his Lieut. Collonel, with Orders to March within two Miles of <hi>Sligo,</hi> where the Enemy kept the Caſtle; they arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there before Day, brought away 400 Cows, 150 Sheep, 80 Goats, and 60 Horſes; the Enemy having taken the Allarm, purſu'd them with two Troops of Horſe, one of Dragoons, and three Companies of Foot, and overtook them within eight Miles of <hi>Belliſhannon,</hi> on which our Forces putting themſelves in the beſt Poſture of Defence, the ſhort time would permit, Attacked the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my with great bravery; and after leſs than half an Hours diſpute, put them to the Rout, killing a Captain, and 16 Souldiers; after which, they brought their Booty clear off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:34476:47"/>
               <head>CHAP IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Cloveſly Shovel</hi> Arrives at <hi>Belfaſt</hi> with Money, Armes, and Ammunition for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. The Famous Action of Sir <hi>Clove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly Shovel</hi> at the <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Dublin</hi> related. <hi>Charlemont</hi> Releived in the Night by Five Hundred <hi>Iriſh.</hi> The Gariſon of <hi>Charlemont</hi> Surprized by an Ambuſcade in the Night. The Governour of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont</hi> demands a Parly, and Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>May 13th.</hi> the Articles of Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Duke views the Situation of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont</hi> and the Garriſon as they March out. <hi>May 15th.</hi> Collonel <hi>Wolſely</hi> with Twelve Hundred Men Beſieges <hi>Bellingar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> raiſes Works againſt it, and beats the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy from their Out Works. Preparations to Storm the Place. The Gariſon hang cut a White Flag, and after Capitulates. The number Killed and Wounded in the Siege.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>APRIL</hi> 12th. Sir <hi>Cloveſly Shovel</hi> in the <hi>Monk,</hi> with ſeveral other Ships under his Command, Arrived at <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> with Men, Arms, and Amunition, and a conſiderable Sum of Money, to Pay the Army. There being a great many ſmall
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34476:47"/>Veſſels in the River of <hi>Dublin</hi> Laden with Hides, Tallow, Frize and other Goods belonging to the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of that City, and Forced from them, in order to be ſent for <hi>France;</hi> of which Sir <hi>Cloueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Shovel</hi> in the <hi>Monk,</hi> having Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of it, the <hi>18th.</hi> of <hi>April</hi> in the Morning, as he was returning from <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt,</hi> he ſtood into the Bay, with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Veſſels in his Company, and ſaw a Ship a Mile within the Bar, at a place call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Polebege,</hi> and being come to an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, Sir <hi>Cloveſly Shovel</hi> went on Board the <hi>Monmouth</hi> Yacht; and at a little more than half Flood, the Wind being Northerly, with the ſaid Yatch, Two Men of War Hoys, a Ketch, and the Pinnaces went over the Bar, upon which the Ship befor-ementioned, removed above a Mile higher, up to <hi>Salmon</hi>-Pool, and there run a-ground, within Shot of a French Man of War, of Twelve Guns, and Two or Three <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships that lay a ground, filled with Souldiers who kept Firing at us: We followed, and attack'd her, and after ſome diſpute, Sir <hi>Cloveſly Shovel</hi> made a Signal for the Fire Ship to come in, which when the Enemy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they forſook the Ship, and got
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34476:48"/>away in their Boats; we went on Board, and got out an Anchor, and by heaving ſome of her things overboard, brought her off. In turning out, the Wind vear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Sea, one of our Hoys ran aground, and we could not get her off, before the Water fell away from her; therefore our Men all lay by her, and got her Anchor out ready to heave off next High Water; at Low Water, the Hoy was on dry Ground, and many Thouſand People came upon the Sands, where was likewiſe the Late King <hi>James:</hi> We lay in our Boats Armed, and Two Proteſtants, among many others that were running about the Sands, at length got to us. The Guards to ſhew their briskneſs, advanced towards us, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, a French-man came Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Water ſide, and called us in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as well as he could, a great many hard Names, and Fired his Piſtols; we Shot his Horſe, and Rowed a Shore: the French Man ſlipt his Legs out of his Boots, and ran away, but the Sailers went a ſhore, and unrigged his Horſe.</p>
               <p>The Ship we took was the <hi>Pelican,</hi> the biggeſt of the two <hi>Scotch</hi> Frigats taken laſt Summer; ſhe had twenty Guns, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34476:48"/>above forty Men; three or four we found dead on the Deck, and one woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; as alſo a <hi>Spaniard</hi> and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, who were forced aboard: They informed Sir <hi>Cloudſly,</hi> that twelve Men were killed, and that ſeveral that went on Shoar were wounded; and that this Frigat lay there to be Convoy to the Veſſels that were Laden with the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> Goods, that the late King <hi>James</hi> was ſending for <hi>France.</hi> This was one of his beſt Men of War. Captain <hi>Wright,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Monmouth</hi> Yacht, was very ſerviceable; for beſides his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the Fleet in, he behaved himſelf very well in the Action, as did all the Officers and Sailors in General, who ſhewed an extraordinary forwardneſs to Engage; and the chief Officers of all the Ships deſired to go in their Boats, expreſſing in this occaſion a great Zeal for Their Majeſties Service.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>22th.</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> in the Night, a Party of between four and five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Rebels, having paſſed the Boggs, which were then in many places dry, got into <hi>Charlemont,</hi> with ſome few Horſes laden with Proviſions. The Sieur <hi>Daveſeant,</hi> Lieutenant Collonel to the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34476:49"/>Regiment of <hi>Cambon,</hi> having notice thereof, and that the Enemy were ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to return to <hi>Caſtle-Blany,</hi> laid part of the ſaid Regiment in Ambuſh, divided into three Parties, under the Command of the Sieur <hi>Vebron,</hi> who acted as Major, Captain <hi>Moutant,</hi> and Captain la <hi>Charroy.</hi> The firſt and ſecond Night the Enemy did not appear, but the third they came out, and happened to fall into the leaſt of our Parties, which was but of forty Men. Captain la <hi>Charroy</hi> who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, perceiving the Enemy, let their Van Guard paſs by, and then ordered his Men to Fire on the main Party, of whom eight, with an Officer were killed, and the reſt fled in great Confuſion towards <hi>Charlemont,</hi> leaving behind them 110 Muſquets, 6 Halbards, 5 Drums, and 60 Hats. So ſoon as 'twas Day, our Men were reinforced by the other Parties, and we found the Enemy (who had rallied) drawn up on a Hill, about a Mile and a half from the Town; they no ſooner ſaw us, but fled again to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Charlemont,</hi> and our Men purſued them as far as the Counterſcarp, and took five Priſoners, and ſeven Horſes, not having loſt one Man on our ſide.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34476:49"/>The ſame Night another Party of the Enemy made a Sally upon an Out-Guard, belonging to la <hi>Callimote</hi>'s Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, of about 40 Men, who retired to a place where were Poſted 60 Men of Collonel <hi>Cutt</hi>'s Regiment, and then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king head againſt the Enemy, beat them back to the Town, killed 9, and took 8 Priſoners, beſides divers Wounded, whom they carried off. On our ſide 3 were killed, and 4 or 5 wounded. An account of theſe Actions being ſent to the General, he immediately ordered two more Regiments of Foot to march forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with and reinforce the Blockade of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont,</hi> in order to keep in the 500 Men that came with the Relief, which did quickly ſtreighten the Garriſon, by ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Proviſions, ſo that in a few days time they were reduced to great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, and on the <hi>11th.</hi> of <hi>May</hi> the Governour of <hi>Charlemont</hi> demanded a Parley, which being granted, with leave to ſend to the General, the Lieutenant-Governour, and a Collonel, went to <hi>Lisburn,</hi> with Orders from that Garriſon, on the <hi>12th;</hi> and the ſame day the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles were agreed upon for the Surrender of that place, as followeth; That all the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34476:50"/>Garriſon, <hi>viz.</hi> the Governour, Officers, Soldiers, Gunners, and all other Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, (the Deſerters who run from us ſince the firſt day of <hi>September</hi> laſt, only excepted,) and all other Perſons in the ſaid Garriſon ſhall have their Lives ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and march out with their Arms, Bag and Baggage, Drums Beating, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours Flying, Match lighted, Bullets in their mouths, each Officer and Soldier 12 Charges of Powder, with Match and Ball proportionable, and their Horſes, without any moleſtation in their Perſons and Goods now in their Poſſeſſion, (not belonging to the Stores) upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever.</p>
               <p>That the ſaid Garriſon may march the neareſt way to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to march above 8 or 9 Miles a Day.</p>
               <p>That all ſick and wounded Officers, and other Perſons that are not able to march at preſent, may remain within the ſaid Garriſon till they are able to march, and then to have a Paſs to go to the next <hi>Iriſh</hi> Garriſon.</p>
               <p>That none of the Army under His Graces Command, ſhall enter the ſaid Fort, except ſuch who are appointed by
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34476:50"/>him to take poſſeſſion of the ſame, 'till the Garriſon be marched clear out of the Gates.</p>
               <p>That there ſhall be a ſufficient Convoy appointed for the ſaid Garriſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct them to the place before-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>That they ſhall deliver fully and wholly, without any imbezlement or diminution, all the Stores belonging to the ſaid Fort; and that an Officer ſhall be immediately admitted to take an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the ſame.</p>
               <p>That the Fort ſhall be put into the Poſſeſſion of ſuch Forces, as his Grace ſhall think fit, at eight of the Clock on <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> being the fourteenth day of <hi>May;</hi> at which Hour the ſaid Garriſon ſhall march out, and an Hour before the outward Gate ſhall be delivered to ſuch Forces as his Grace ſhall appoint; in caſe a ſupply of one Months Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for eight Hundred Men be not brought into the Gariſon for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, between the ſigning hereof, and the ſaid time.</p>
               <p>That the above-mentioned Articles ſhall be inviolably performed on both ſides, without any Equivocation, Mental
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34476:51"/>Reſervation, or Fraud whatſoever, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to true intent and meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, That all Acts of Hoſtility ſhall ceaſe between the ſaid Gariſon and Army, ſo ſoon as notice can be given on both ſides.</p>
               <p>In purſuance of this Capitulation, the Governour <hi>Teage o Regan,</hi> and the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon (who had almoſt conſumed all their Proviſions) marched out on the <hi>14th</hi> Inſtant, 800 ſtrong, leaving in the place a good quantity of Ammunition, and 17 Pieces of Braſs Cannon, and two Mortars. His Grace the Duke of <hi>Schon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> went to <hi>Legacury,</hi> to ſee the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as they marched away, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards viſited <hi>Charlemont,</hi> which is very ſtrong and conſiderable by its Situation, four Companies of Collonel <hi>Babington</hi>'s Regiment were put into Gariſon</p>
               <p>On the <hi>16th</hi> his Grace, our General, received a Letter from Collonel <hi>Wolſely,</hi> given an account of the taking the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Bellingargy,</hi> near <hi>Cavan,</hi> as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:34476:51"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>Belturbet, <date>May <hi>14.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>ON <hi>Monday</hi> Night laſt, I marched out of this Town, with a Detachment of <hi>1200</hi> Men; and the next Morning I came before the Caſtle of <hi>Bellingargy,</hi> which place I found much ſtronger than it had been repreſented to me, and no man but an Iriſh-man would have been beaten out of it without Cannon, which I wanting, I betook my ſelf to the only way left to reduce it; which was to make Blinds, and raiſe Works behind them to overlook the Enemies; and ſo the whole day was ſpent in making them, and the Faſcines, 'till four in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and then all things being ready, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Foulkes,</hi> with a Detachment of Foot, ſet upon a Party of the Enemy that were Poſted in an Iſland in the River, under the Caſtle, in which place we determined (if poſſible) to raiſe our Works; but the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Flying as ſoon as we ſet upon them, our Men inſtead of falling to their Work, purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them up to their Trenches, and would not be got off; and the Enemy lying hard upon them, I ordered ſome Detachments to give the Enemy a diverſion on the other ſide of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34476:52"/>the Caſtle, by making a falſe Attack: Theſe, as ſoon as they received the Orders, preſſed the place with as much heat as the others had done, and beat the Enemy out of a Ravelin, which was raiſed before the Draw-bridge, and Fired upon them through their own Spike holes, that the Enemy were forced to quit moſt of their Works in ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which as ſoon as I perceiv'd, I ordered the Horſe and Dragoons to bring up all the Faſcines to the brim of the Ditch, and began to fill up the Ditch; which the Enemy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, they hung out a white Flag; and after ſome time ſpent in Capitulation, we came to this Agreement. That they ſhould have Quarter for Life, and be conveyed to the next Gariſon; but they left their Arms behind them, with all their Ammunition and Stores, which was but two Barrels and a half of Powder, and one and a half of Ball: The Garriſon was four Companies conſiſting of ſome what more then <hi>200</hi> Men. I had the ill Fortune, in the heat of the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, to be ſhot in the Belly; but ſo favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that I hope, in few days, I ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to get on Horſe-back again; though I was forced to with draw out of the Fight, as ſoon as I was Wounded; but my Poſt was ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Collonel <hi>Foulke,</hi> who managed the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34476:52"/>Aſſault with great Bravery, and greater Conduct than ever I could pretend to. This is the ſtrongeſt place I have ever ſeen in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> the Rampart is ſo high, that it is a difficult matter to get up, though none there to keep one out, which made me the willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to take it upon Terms, becauſe I ſaw it would unavoidably coſt me a great many Men to take it by force; the beat of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers running on without Orders, made it coſt me much dearer than I expected, The Account of what we have loſt, is as followeth: Killed out of Collonel <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Regiment <hi>4</hi> Soldiers, and <hi>16</hi> more Wounded; with an Enſign killed out of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Battalion, <hi>1</hi> Captain, and <hi>4</hi> Soldiers; and <hi>1</hi> Captain, <hi>3</hi> Serjeants, and <hi>14</hi> Soldiers wounded. Out of Collonel <hi>Foulkes</hi> Regiment, Captain <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bois</hi> killed, with <hi>3</hi> Gentlemen that carried Arms, and <hi>6</hi> Soldiers, and <hi>10</hi> wounded.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:34476:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Brief Accounts of the Tranſactions of the Late King <hi>James,</hi> towards the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> in ſeveral parts of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The ſham Pardon of the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Bandon,</hi> and the Cruelty after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards uſed towards them. The Tranſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Earl of <hi>Seaforth,</hi> Sir R. <hi>Neagle,</hi> and Sir <hi>Tho. Southwel.</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Cruelties towards the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at <hi>Limrick</hi> and <hi>Dublin.</hi> The ſeveral ſham Proclamations to enſnare the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi> The particular Invoice of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Goods ſeized in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſent to the <hi>French</hi> King. The late King's ſeizing the Farmers Bread-Corn, to the almoſt ſtarving of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. The Inhumane and Barbarous U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at <hi>Galway,</hi> by Order of the late King. The Raviſhing of the Farmer's Daughter in <hi>Dublin,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Noon-day, before her Fathers Face. The Murthering three <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Clothiers i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Suburbs of <hi>Dublin.</hi> The Cruelti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> of the <hi>French</hi> towards the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE late King, at his firſt Arrival in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ingratiate himſelf with the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and to beget an opinion
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34476:53"/>of his great Clemency among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he very graciouſly condeſcended t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grant a general and free Pardon to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Bandon,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſing them with an aſſurance of an a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Indemnity for their Tranſgreſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but ſoon after he remitted them to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> ſeverity of the Law, and expoſed the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to a Tryal for their Lives, upon whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they were all found Guilty of Hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Treaſon; and no other Conſeque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> could rationally be expected, when b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> Judges and Jury were compoſed of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorable <hi>Papiſts:</hi> And in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> time this mighty Crime was no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> than that the Inhabitants of the Place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving their Neighbours to be op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> Rob'd and Pillag'd, and from Clandeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> Thievery to proceed to violent De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, they thought it prudent to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their Gates, and avoid Plunder by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Defence and Self-preſervation.</p>
               <p>This was the firſt Eſſay of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Indulgence of a <hi>Popiſh</hi> King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Proteſtant Subjects: This was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Specimen of what is to be exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> from him who will mortgage his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the humour of his Prieſts.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:34476:54"/>
               <p>The buſineſs of Sir <hi>Thomas Southwel</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>together of another Nature; and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>e repetition of it may juſtly cauſe an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>horrence of thoſe Blood-ſuckers, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>light in the torment and ruin of ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> call <hi>Hereticks;</hi> ſo the Example may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>moniſh all Men of State and Degree, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to truckle their Authority in Vaſſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> to their Servants and Inferiours.</p>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Seaforth</hi> taking a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> fancy to Sir <hi>Thomas Southwel,</hi> a very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>eful young Gentleman (and under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>demnation for his reputed Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> procur'd a Warrant from the Late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>g to Sir <hi>Richard Neagle</hi> his Attorney-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>eral, to paſs a Pardon for him, which ſaid Earl ſhewed to Sir <hi>Richard;</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a moſt unmannerly and churliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>on refuſed to obey it; ſaying, it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> than the King could do. The Earl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ed to his Maſter, and reported the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>er of the Attorney-General; who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſent for owned it to the King, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ly told him, It was not in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to grant him a Pardon; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> the King paſſionately locked him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> in his Cloſet.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> who in <hi>England</hi> was flattered into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>it of an abſolute and unlimitted
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34476:54"/>Power to diſpence with the eſtabliſhed Laws; is not allowed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg inherent to all Soveraign Powers, by the Law of Nations, to pardon the Offences of a Subject. But even in this it has appeared (as by ſeveral other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances) that he is permitted to pardon any Crime in a Roman Catholick, but in relation to a Proteſtant, the Law is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenable.</p>
               <p>And what favour Proteſtants are to expect under a Popiſh King, and in a Kingdom where Popery is predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; let all men judge by their proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where almoſt all the Churches (where the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Arms were prevalent) except in <hi>Dublin,</hi> were ſeized by Authority, the Proteſtant Miniſters were Deprived, and Popiſh Prieſts ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and inducted into Livings, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Preferments.</p>
               <p>It is a matter not unworthy the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; how dexterouſly the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there could prevaricate in their dealings with the poor enſlaved Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; For upon any apprehention of Succours arriving from <hi>England,</hi> or other pretext to fleece and ſqueeze them,; an Information was preſently given, how
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34476:55"/>numerous the Proteſtants were, and what danger may ariſe from thence; and then they were forthwith confined, and hurried away to Priſon, and their Houſes and Goods expoſed to the Rapine of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French:</hi> At another time, when it might be ſubſervient to their deſigns, to leſſen the number, and underval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue the ſtrength of the Proteſtants; then they give out that their number was but ſmall, and their intereſt inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: And this is very remarkable in a late Paſſage. at the City of <hi>Limorick,</hi> where the Cabal of the Papiſts project<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to get the Churches (there) into their Hands, Repreſented to the King and Council, that the Proteſtants in that Place were ſo very few, that there was no need to Aſſign them any more then one Church for their Meeting; and this Suggeſtion was fortifyed by a Letter from the Earl of <hi>Limmerick,</hi> atteſting the ſame.</p>
               <p>If at any time an Information was given to the Government of any Mony, Plate, or other things valuable in the hands of a Proteſtant, tho guarded by the ſolemnity of a Protection; this was ſoon ſeconded by the ſuſpection of ſome
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34476:55"/>Plot againſt the Government, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately a Party was ſent to ſeize their Perſons, to Search and Plunder their Houſes; and ſo after the Infliction of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orts of Miſery and Diſtreſs, they are admitted to Liberty, under the Caution of Bonds for good behaviour; but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left to ſuſtain them, or to prevent the Calamitous Aſſaults of Poverty and Famine: At another time they proceed with a more Jeſuitical Fierceneſs, for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Eye a concealed purchaſe of Money, or good Moveables, in the Hands of a Proteſtant; immediately an Order was ſecretly Granted to ſeize the Perſons, and ſecure their Goods; and then to amuſe the World with an Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Juſtice and Lenity; a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation was contrived with a plauſible promiſe of Indemnity, to all Proteſtants under their Protection, and an invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all Men, to reſt ſecure under the Benignity of it: But in the mean time the matter is ſo ordered, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation ſhall not be Publiſhed, nor delivered into the Sherriffs Hands, or other Officers, tho anti-dated before the Iſſuing ſuch Order, till a certain Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34476:56"/>be receiv'd, that the Order is Executed, and the Work done.</p>
               <p>What a miſerable and an unexpected Oppreſſion is it, that the poor Subjects ſhall be compelled to part with their Goods and Merchandiſe for a contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible lump of Braſs, or Pewter? Yet ſuch ever hath been the conſtant proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Late King towards his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>Ireland;</hi> whoſe Goods and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities he rather Seizeth than Buyeth, and becoming the grand Merchant of the Kingdom, he is the general in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſer of all Trade, which he Vents and Exports to his dear Correſpondent in <hi>France:</hi> Bargaining with the Owner at ſuch a rate, as the Buyer is pleaſed to make, and diſcharging his Contract in Bills of Copper, Pewter, and Braſs, which can in no way avail the poor Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or ſupport him in the circulation of his Trade. I will only preſent the <hi>Reader</hi> with one inſtance (among innumerable others) and give him an Authentick Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what Goods were taken up in <hi>Dublin</hi> at one time, for the Kings uſe, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> were ſeized by Armed Force, and a Price ſet upon them, at the pleaſure of the Taker.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:34476:56"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>Seized in the City of <hi>Dublin</hi> for the King's uſe, <hi>February 6. 1689.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Tann'd Hides.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Raw Hides.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Stones of Wool at 18 <hi>ps</hi> in the Stone.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Tuns of Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>ſtones of But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>In <hi>Oxmantown.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>00920</cell>
                        <cell>02140</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>St. <hi>Andrew</hi>'s, St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, and St. <hi>Brides.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>1166</cell>
                        <cell>02190</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>St. <hi>Catherins,</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi> and St. <hi>Nichol.</hi> without.</cell>
                        <cell>05071</cell>
                        <cell>03192</cell>
                        <cell>61105</cell>
                        <cell>389</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Within the City.</cell>
                        <cell>11619</cell>
                        <cell>07192</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="total">18771.</cell>
                        <cell role="total">14687.</cell>
                        <cell role="total">61105.</cell>
                        <cell role="total">389.</cell>
                        <cell role="total">40.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>This with much more, (about the time Sir <hi>Cloveſly Shovel</hi> ſtood before <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi>) was a carrying on Board the Ships that lay in the Harbour, to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported to <hi>France;</hi> which for that ſmall time, Sir <hi>Cloveſly Shovel</hi> tarried there, had ſome intermiſſion; but as ſoon as he was gone, the ſame, and many more hands were employed, that all might be ſent off; whilſt the like methods were a putting in Execution in all parts of the Country, ſeizing and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying away what the Proteſtants had, in order to be ſent after the former, by the next opportunity; beggering the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34476:57"/>and Impoveriſhing the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by a wilful Devaſtation of thoſe ſtaple Commodities, for which no other return could be expected, (none elſe being promiſed) but materials to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the remainder of the poor unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Proteſtants, under their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The Country being well ſtor d with Grane of all ſorts, eſpecially the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys about <hi>Dublin,</hi> whereof the Gen ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Inhabitants are Proteſtants; a very plauſible Proclamation was iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out to encourage the Farmers, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and furniſh the Markets, which when they had for ſome time frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, another Proclamation came forth, ſetting a preciſe Rate (but much lower then the common Market price) upon all kinds of Grane, Proviſions, and other Merchantable Commodities, conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Seller to part with his Goods at the Rates preſcribed, on pain of looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all without a ſatisfaction; or in plain Engliſh, to ſeize on Men's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties and effects, under pretence and colour of furniſhing the King's Stores.</p>
               <p>After the late King had made Braſs Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney current in <hi>Ireland,</hi> it was at firſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34476:57"/>pretended to paſs only in Payments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Man and Man in their daily Commerce and Dealings, and in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick payment in Duties to the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer. But ſoon after, the Iriſh begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to conſider, that they were gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Indepted to the Engliſh, and that this might be a fit ſeaſon, and a lucky opportunity to get their Debts eaſily and cheaply diſcharged, a Proclamation was publiſhed, enjoyning and requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Copper and Braſs Money ſhould paſs as current Money within the Realm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the payment of Bills, Bonds, Debts by Record, Mortgages, and all other Payments whatſoever. By which knack, many a poor Proteſtant was fob'd out of his Right, and compelled to take a heap of Traſh for his Debt, (as he was for his Wheat and other Commodities, or be precluded from any further Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And thus Collonel <hi>Roger Moore</hi> was ſerv'd, who having an Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of 3000 <hi>p.</hi> upon the Lord <hi>Dillar</hi>'s Eſtate, who is married to a Daughter of the Lord or Lady <hi>Tyrconnel;</hi> ſhe ſent for him, and told him, that having ſome Money at her command, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34476:58"/>being very deſirous to take off the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then from her Daughters Eſtate, ſhe was content to pay him off in ready Moneys, provided he would make ſome handſome abatement of the Sumn due. The Gentleman being complaiſſant to the Lady, and very willing to receive Money in ſuch a time of ſcarcety, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſented to abate a thouſand Pound, ſo the reſt might be paid down at once: The Lady ſeemed very thankful, and appointed him to come next day, and bring the Deeds and Obligations with him, and ſo receive his Money. Accordingly he came, and having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a Legal Releaſe; the Lady opened a Door, and ſhewed him along Table, covered over with Copper and Braſs, and tendred it for his Payment, which whether he rejected it in paſſion, or hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Cart to carry it away, I cannot tell; but this I can ſay, having an Eſtate which was Mortgaged to the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor, before 1641. to which on Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Mortgage Money, he hoped to be roſtored by Repealing the Acts of Settlement; he repaired to me, and deſired me to appoint time, and place for Payment of the Mortgage Money,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34476:58"/>of which, I have taken time to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. One of the moſt eminent Silver Smiths of <hi>Dublin,</hi> having ſold all his Plate to a Papiſt, who promiſed to pay him his price (agreed upon) in Silver and Gold; but no faith being to be kept with Hereticks, the Gold-Smith was compelled to take Braſs and Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ſoon after this, the late King put out his Savoury and Fruitful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, to make Braſs Money paſs in Satisfaction of all Debts, ſigned at <hi>Dublin</hi> Caſtle, <hi>February 4th,</hi> 1689.</p>
               <p>They were grown ſo ſevere to the poor Proteſtants, that they would not ſuffer them to buy a Loaf of Bread from a Baker, but at the ſecond hand from the Soldiers, and were forced to pay a treble rate for it; and even that liberty was reſtrained, when the French came to be Garriſoned in <hi>Dublin;</hi> ſo that I fear, that many of them were ſtarved in the ſtreets.</p>
               <p>But I challenge all Hiſtories and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of Nations, to parallel the late ſhameful uſage of the poor Proteſtant Priſoners in <hi>Galway,</hi> upon whom was placed ſo odious a Cheat, ſo unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Sham, that poſterity will hardly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34476:59"/>be induced to believe it; and I muſt implore the Charity of the preſent Age, not to look upon it as a Fable; but it is ſo certain, and ſo ſad a truth, that I defie the Subtility and Impudence of a Jeſuit to gainſay, or contradict it. There was a Stipulation made not long ſince, between the late King <hi>James,</hi> and the French Tyrant, to exchange ſome Regiments of Auxillaries, and about 5000 Men being accordingly ſent from <hi>France,</hi> and Landed in <hi>Ireiand,</hi> the late King ordered the like number of Iriſh to be forthwith embarked, and tranſported into <hi>France,</hi> under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Major General <hi>Mac-Carte,</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom they would do great feats, as by experience, the Inniskilling Men,) among whom, the Regiment under the command of Coll. <hi>Robert Fielding,</hi> known by the name of handſome <hi>Field<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> was appointed to be one; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could get his Regiment on board, a great number of the Men run away, according to their natural and uſual cuſtom; ſo that he became mightily puzzled, what ſhift to make to recruit his Regiment, whereupon this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient way found out: There was in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:34476:59"/>
                  <hi>Galway</hi> about 120 Priſoners, (who had been ſeized for endeavouring to make their eſcape with Sir <hi>T. Southwell</hi> out of the Iriſh Quarters;) and who had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the miſeries of cloſe Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Cold, Hungry, and a daily Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a violent Death for above 14 Months, lying under Condemnation for pretended Treaſon: To them Coll. <hi>Fielding</hi> applied himſelf, and propoſed to them, that for every one of them that would raiſe 8 Men, and deliver them to him to recruit his Regiment, ſuch ſhould not only have their imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Liberty, but an abſolute Pardon for all that was paſt; and to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he produced a Warrant for a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Pardon; the poor Gentlemen overjoyed with the ſecurity of their Lives, and the Proſpect of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, conſented readily to the Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and with all earneſtneſs betook themſelves to the performance of what was expected on their parts, and in a very ſhort time about 14 of the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers brought in the number demanded of them, and delivered them to the Conduct of the Collonel, who carried on the Intreague without Suſpition;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34476:60"/>but alaſs the poor unfortunate Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men having accompliſhed their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, with extraordinary Pains and Charges, being obliged to pay great ſums of Money to thoſe Mercinary Men; no ſooner was the Collonel with his Men ſhipt away, but an order was ſent from the late King, to ſeize upon thoſe deluded Gentlemen, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commit them to their former Priſon, on pretence of the Contract made with them by Collonel <hi>Fielding,</hi> was not done with his Allowance; the Great Turk would bluſh to be charged with ſuch an Action, and a very Heathen would abhor it; an Action fit only for the Monſieur of <hi>France,</hi> and ſuch Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are influenced by his Example.</p>
               <p>The French as they paſt by any of our Clergy in <hi>Dublin,</hi> threatned them ſadly on which the Clergy held frequent Conſultations how to ſecure themſelves, and delivered their poor Flocks from the daily Threats and Menaces of the French Vultures. It was moved that the Clergy ſhould diſguiſe themſelves in Frieze Coats, not finding it probable to eſcape the then impending Dangers in their Gowns; this motion was reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:34476:60"/>by the Majority, and ſtill depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his Protection, who ſtills the Winds, and the raging of the Seas.</p>
               <p>The French had not been two days in <hi>Dublin,</hi> when they murdered two or three Proteſtant Cloathiers, in a part of the City, call'd the <hi>Comb;</hi> for that great Crime of protecting their Wives from being made Proſtitutes to the French; of which Inhumane act, no notice was ever taken by the late King or his Government, more than if two Dogs had been ſhot. About the ſame time, ſome of them took a Country Maid that came to Market with her Father, and defloured her in the open ſtreets at Noon-day. Many ſuch barbarous pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Villany has been perpetrated by thoſe Blood-ſuckers, whoſe continual Practice was in all parts of the World where they have been, to burn and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh ſuch Places as were not tenable by them; and ſo they moved in their Councils, that famous City of <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> ſhould be dealt with; firſt, to ſhut up the Proteſtants in the Churches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals, and then if they loſt the day, to ſet fire to all; whereby, not only the City, but the Proteſtants alſo would be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:34476:61"/>deſtroyed; whereupon the Iriſh Papiſts Traders in the City, and thoſe of the Army, that either themſelves, Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Friends, owned Houſes in it, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd themſelves to their King, and told him they ſhould ſuffer in that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, as well as the Proteſtants; and that they would not draw a Sword in his defence, unleſs all thoughts of burning the City were ſet aſide, and declared, that as ſoon as they ſaw, or heard of any appearance of Fire, they would fly from his Seruice, and ſubmit to King <hi>William</hi>'s Mercy; of which, now they have had a good experiment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Great Plunder taken by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> near <hi>Finagh</hi> and <hi>Kells, 27</hi> Miles of <hi>Dublin. Caſtle-Blany</hi> and ſeveral Villages burnt. The Rebels break down the Bridges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Newry and Dundalk.</hi> Duke <hi>Schonberg</hi> goes to <hi>Belfaſt</hi> the <hi>14 June,</hi> expecting the King. <hi>June 15.</hi> The King lands at <hi>Carrickfergus.</hi> His great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in all places, with ſeveral addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes preſented to him. <hi>June 24</hi> His
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34476:61"/>Majeſty goes to <hi>Newry.</hi> A Camp is there form'd. The King's Meſſage to the Iriſh. The Iriſh quit <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and retires to <hi>Ardee.</hi> The whole Engliſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Encamps on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk.</hi> The Iriſh quit <hi>Ardee,</hi> poſt themſelves on the <hi>Boyne. June 30th,</hi> The King En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camps within ſight of the Iriſh Army. Is wounded with a Cannon Ball, viewing the the Enemies Camp. <hi>July 1.</hi> Part of the Engliſh Army paſſes the <hi>Boyne.</hi> The whole Iriſh Army defeated, and retires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their King to <hi>Dublin.</hi> The Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Dublin</hi> on the Approach of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Army. King <hi>James</hi> retires to <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford.</hi> The Engliſh Army Encamp at <hi>Finglaſs,</hi> from whence the King goes to <hi>Dublin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAY</hi> 18. One of our Parties of 80 Horſe and Dragoons, moſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh that were Quartered about <hi>Hils<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> went within a Mile of <hi>Finnaugh,</hi> and took 5 Priſoners and 80 Horſes, and ſeveral hundred head of Cattle. The Enemy ſallied out of the Town of <hi>Finnaugh</hi> with 100 Horſe, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving juſt ſhewed themſelves, returned in again, and our Men marched away quietly with their Booty.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:34476:62"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>May</hi> 23. Collonel <hi>Wolſely</hi> detached a Party of 100 Foot, 36 Horſe, and ſome Dragoons, they went as far as <hi>Kells,</hi> within 27 Miles of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and brought back a good booty, Cows, Sheep and Horſes, without meeting with any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. This day news came to the General, that the Rebels had burnt <hi>Caſtle-Blany,</hi> and ſeveral other Villages thereabouts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> 6. The <hi>Count de Schonberg</hi> arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Belfaſt</hi> with Forces, Arms and Amunition, and likewiſe 200 Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Smiths, and other Artificers for the Service of the Army.</p>
               <p>One Captain <hi>Smith,</hi> formerly of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalk,</hi> went by the general order on the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> with a Party of Horſe from the <hi>Newry,</hi> to review the Roads thence to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and found all the Bridge and Cauſayes broke, to preven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our march; all the Roads betwixt <hi>Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourne</hi> and the <hi>Newry,</hi> and from thence towards <hi>Dundalk,</hi> were immediately or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be mended, and vaſt quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Proviſions and Stores were day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſent towards <hi>Ardmagh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The General expecting the King Landing, came to <hi>Belfaſt</hi> the 14th in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34476:62"/>in the Afternoon, and ſent out Men to all the adjacent Coaſts to watch; and at nine that Night, the Poſt of <hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noghedee</hi> coming with the Pacquet, brought advice, the King had paſſed by that place towards <hi>Belfaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next day being <hi>Saturday,</hi> about three in the Afternoon, the General received advice, His Majeſty was come into the <hi>Lough;</hi> and thereupon in his Coach, and Sett of ſmall black <hi>Barbery</hi> Horſes, poſted away to meet the King at <hi>Carrickfergus;</hi> His Majeſty on his Landing, immediately mounted, and rode on Horſeback through the main ſtreet of the Town, where the almoſt numberleſs crowds of People bid His Majeſty welcome, with continual ſhouts and Acclamations at the White-Houſe, three miles hence, half way betwixt this and <hi>Carrickfergus;</hi> the General met the King at four of the Clock, who was pleaſed for to alight, and go into his Coach, attended only with one Troop of Horſe, and a few Gentlemen, and immediately drove over the <hi>Strand</hi> hither.</p>
               <p>The uncertainty of the time, and place of His Majeſties Landing; and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34476:63"/>the ſuddenneſs of the News was ſuch, that few of the Multitude that flocked hither to ſee it, had their ends, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals motion was ſo quick; yet before they got into the Town, there were abundance that met them, and coming to the North-Gate, he was received by the Soveraign, and Burgeſſes of <hi>Belfaſt</hi> in their Formalities, a Guard of the Foot Guards, and a general continued Shout and Shouts of, God ſave the King, God bleſs our Proteſtant King, God bleſs King <hi>William.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being come to the Caſtle, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty alighted, and with the General walked into, and round a very fine Garden at the back ſide thereof.</p>
               <p>Then His Majeſty went into an Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment appointed for him, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately iſſued out Orders for bringing aſhore 200000 <hi>l.</hi> which came with him into the <hi>Lough,</hi> and 15 Tuns of Half-Pence, and Farthings in Tin, and that an Account be forthwith ſent to the Agents of all Regiments, to bring in their Accompts within three Days, in order to receive their Mens pay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In order to which, His Majeſty preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fell upon Meaſures how to clear all
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34476:63"/>Quarters, and diſcharge the Country, and ordered the Train to be ready to march in a Week. As the King was coming over the <hi>Strand,</hi> another Coach of the Generals met him, which his Grace called too out of the former, and ordered ſtreight forward to the White-Houſe, to receive into it ſuch perſons of Quality as they ſhould find firſt Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Not far from the ſaid North-gate, His Majeſty was met by Dr. <hi>George Walker,</hi> late Governour of <hi>London Derry,</hi> and about twelve of the Epiſcopal Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, who followed the Coach to the Caſtle, and when His Majeſty alighted, Addreſſed him in a Congratulatory Speech on his Arival.</p>
               <p>At Night the Streets were filled with Bonfire-Works, which were no ſooner lighted, but the Allarm Signal was given by diſcharge of Guns, ſo planted, that from one place to another throughout the whole Country in our hands in a few Minutes, all places had notice of the King's Arival, and in three Hours made Bonfiers ſo thick, that the whole Country ſeemed in a flame. So that the Enemy could not but ſee, and conjecture the cauſe to their Eternal Grief.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:34476:64"/>
               <p>At <hi>Lisbourne,</hi> One <hi>George Gregſon,</hi> the moſt eminent Preaching Quaker in the Province of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Bonfire, the Soldiers broke all his Windows, pull'd down the Pales round his Houſe, forc'd his Wheel-barrows, Shovels, Pick-Axes, Tubs, Pitch and Tar Barrels out of his backſide, and piled them up before his Door in a ſtately Bonfire; and had not his Houſe been Lieutenant General <hi>Doug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſs</hi>'s Quarters, it had been impoſſible to ſave it from pulling down, ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry were the People.</p>
               <p>On the 16th, Lieutenant General <hi>Douglaſs</hi> came hither; as likewiſe a great number of Presbyterian Miniſters, who came to wait on His Majeſty, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him with a Loyal Addreſs. A little after the Kings landing at the <hi>Lough,</hi> betwixt <hi>Carrickfergus</hi> and <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> ſeem'd to be like a Wood, there being in it no leſs then between 6 or 700 Sail of Ships, moſt loaden with Proviſions and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition; the Plenty and Order of all things there was moſt wonderful, and not credible to any, but thoſe that ſaw it, no Army in <hi>Chriſtondom</hi> the like, and yet all Goods held a good Rate, Bear 13
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34476:64"/>or 14 pound the Tun, Claret and White-wine, 15 pound the Hogſhead, Canaries and Sherries, 10 <hi>s.</hi> a Gallon, Malaga, and right good Brandy, 8 <hi>s.</hi> a Gallon, Wheat 1 <hi>p.</hi> 5 <hi>s.</hi> the <hi>Briſtol</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, Mault 17 <hi>s.</hi> a Larrel, Flowers 15 <hi>d.</hi> the Stone, Cheeſe 1 <hi>p.</hi> 15 <hi>s.</hi> the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, Salt 1 <hi>s.</hi> the Gallon, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable for all other Goods for Back and Belly.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty continued at <hi>Belfaſt</hi> till <hi>June</hi> 19. at which time he went to <hi>Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn,</hi> and dined with the General, and the ſame Night he went to <hi>Hilsbrough,</hi> accompanied with Prince <hi>George,</hi> Lord General <hi>Douglaſs,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and a great many other Nobility and Gentry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> 20. This Day Landed at the <hi>White-Houſe,</hi> 2500 Horſe from <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> a Camp is now forming near <hi>Tanderagee,</hi> about 20 Miles South from <hi>Lisbourne</hi> and on the very Frontiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Ardmagh</hi> and the <hi>Newry,</hi> whither all the Army is marching.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:34476:65"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>The following Addreſs was humbly. preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Majeſty upon his Arrival in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>GReateſt of Kings, conquer what is your own,</l>
                  <l>And add poor <hi>Irel.</hi> to ſweet <hi>Engl.</hi> Crown,</l>
                  <l>Pull the Stift neck of every Papiſt down;</l>
                  <l>Set Captives free, who on the Willow Trees,</l>
                  <l>Hang uſeleſs Harps that tun'd ſuch Songs as theſe.</l>
                  <l>Ah! Mighty Prince, how do our Sorrows ſwell,</l>
                  <l>What Tongues, or Pens, can our great Miſeries tell,</l>
                  <l>Who in the midſt of <hi>Satan</hi>'s Subjects dwell?</l>
                  <l>Diſarm'd, and Plunder'd, Captiv'd here we lie,</l>
                  <l>Gladly we would, alaſs but cannot fly.</l>
                  <l>Iriſh and French inſult, Triumph and Kill,</l>
                  <l>And who dare ſay the Ruffians have done ill,</l>
                  <l>Since all their Law is Couched in their <hi>Will?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Papiſts Locuſts do the Church devour,</l>
                  <l>Raviſh our Wives, and our young Maids deflour;</l>
                  <l>Ariſe, Great Sir, and like a Rampant Lion,</l>
                  <l>Revenge the Affronts of poor diſtreſſed <hi>Sion;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bleſt be the Angel, brings the beſt of Kings,</l>
                  <l>With Expedition on the Cherub's Wings;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt be the Wind and Tide that waſts you o're,</l>
                  <l>To your ſad Subjects on the Iriſh ſhoar:</l>
                  <l>And ever bleſs'd be they that Fight your Cau'e,</l>
                  <l>And with their Swords maintain Great <hi>Britain</hi>'s Laws</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:34476:65"/>
               <p>On the 22. of <hi>June,</hi> His Majeſty went from <hi>Hilsbrough,</hi> to the Town of <hi>Newry,</hi> where he viewed the part of his Army that was encamped there, conſiſting of 24000 Horſe, Foot and Dragoons, His Majeſty being informed by his Scouts there, that the Iriſh Forces with their King, were come to a Paſs within four Miles of the <hi>Newry,</hi> betwixt that and the Town of <hi>Dundalk;</hi> His Majeſty ſent a Trumpeter to acquaint the Iriſh, that in caſe they burnt any more Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, He had given order to His Army that they ſhould not give Quarter to a Man, either French or Iriſh they ſhould meet with. And that very Night His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty gave Order for 500 Horſe and Dragoons to be Detached, under the Command of Lieutenant Gen. <hi>Schrave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> to march towards <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and mark out a place to Encamp in; the Iriſh ſeeing ſome of the Horſe that were the advanc'd Guard, appear, and they thinking the whole Army was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, immediately quitted their Paſs, and fled to <hi>Ardee,</hi> burning their Tents for haſte, but left the Town ſtanding, being apprehenſive that the King would be as good as his word,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:34476:66"/>ſome of our advanced Party march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo near the Enemy, that they plainly ſaw them ſet Fire to their Tents, and the confuſion they were in.</p>
               <p>The Paſſes being clear, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty immediately advanced with the Forces from the <hi>Newry</hi> towards <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalk,</hi> and ſent orders for General <hi>Douglaſs</hi>'s, and the other Forces to change their march before deſigned them, and immediately to march, and joyn him at <hi>Dundalk:</hi> On the 27th, we Encamped on the Plains of <hi>Dundalk,</hi> where we reſted the next day, and underſtood that the Enemy were retired from <hi>Ardee,</hi> and had Poſted themſelves on the South ſide of the River <hi>Boyne;</hi> the King went him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf beyond <hi>Ardee,</hi> to view the ground, and on the 29th, he marched thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and on the 30th, His Majeſty Encamped in ſight of the Enemy, the River <hi>Boyn</hi> being between us and them; the King's Tent was pitched about a Mile ſhort of the <hi>Boyne,</hi> and as much above <hi>Drogheda.</hi> His Majeſty at his Arival near the River,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:34476:66"/>about Noon rode in full view of the Iriſh Army, which lay encampt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards on the other ſide. The Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſoon diſcovered it muſt be His Majeſty who was ſo attended, which made them draw down two pieces of ſix pound Ball from the Forts a little higher, and planted them oppoſite to the place where our Horſe was drawn up, they preſently began to fire, and one of the Balls paſſed ſo cloſe to His Majeſty, that it took away a piece of his Coat, Waſtcoat and Shirt, raiſed the Skin on the blade of his Right Shoulder, and drew a little Blood; but a Plaiſter being put on, His Majeſty continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Horſeback without the leaſt concerne, till four in the Afternoon, when he dined, and in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was on Horſeback again, though he had been up from one in the Morning. The Enemy ſpent about two hundred Balls, and killed us four or five Men, and about ten Horſes; for it was here that our Horſe ſtood the ſhot of the Enemy, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man on foot by his Horſe ſeveral
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:34476:67"/>hours, while there paſs'd the Shot before mentioned. At laſt when the King had ſaid, <hi>Now I ſee my Men will ſtand,</hi> ſome Guns were ſent to our Horſe, and about five in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we brought ſome of our Guns to bear, and diſmounted one of theirs, and with our Bombs, beat down ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Tents, next adjoyning to thoſe of the late King <hi>James,</hi> and the <hi>Count de Lauzun.</hi> His Majeſty reſted very well at Night, and at Eight the next Morning, being <hi>July</hi> 1. was again-on Horſeback; and while the great Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets were flying, the Prince of <hi>Derm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadts</hi> Horſe was ſhot in the Neck. By a Proteſtant Deſerter that ſwam over the River laſt night, we were informed, that the Enemy were 25000 ſtrong, that they had ſent away ſome of their heavieſt Baggage, in order (as they gave out) to Fight us. The King commanded the <hi>Count de Schon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> to march with all the Horſe and Dragoons of the firſt and ſecond Line of the Right Wing, and the Brigade of <hi>Trelawney,</hi> and to paſs the River about four Miles from the Camp, in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:34476:67"/>order to take the Enemy in Flank, while the reſt of our Army paſſed it nearer <hi>Drogheda,</hi> over againſt their Camp; which the Enemy perceiving, they marched part of their Army to oppoſe the <hi>Count de Schonberge,</hi> (who had already broke ſome of their Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of Horſe, and Dragoons that advanced to hinder his paſſing the River) and drew them up in Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia about a Mile and a half from the place where he had paſſed the River. The King being informed of what had paſſed on that ſide, ſent Licutenant General <hi>Douglaſs</hi> with two Brigades of Foot, to re-inforce the <hi>Count d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Schonberg,</hi> who thereupon changed his Order of Battle, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Wing of Horſe on his Right, and another on his Left, and placing the Foot in the middle. In this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture he marched towards the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, whom he found drawn up in Batalia, and charging the Enemy, after ſome ſmall Reſiſtance, put them into diſorder, and followed them Fighting as far as the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage called <hi>Duleek.</hi> The Earl of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:34476:68"/>
                  <hi>Portland,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Overkirke</hi> had part in this Action as <hi>Mareſchals de</hi> Camp.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the King cauſed the reſt of the Foot of the firſt Line, conſiſting of the Brigades of <hi>la Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere,</hi> which was on the Right, of <hi>Hanmer,</hi> and the Danes to march.</p>
               <p>The three Batalions of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Guards were at the head of them, and paſſed the Ford on the Right, over againſt the Village before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, from whence they beat the Enemy that were poſted there. The Battalion of <hi>la Meloniere</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them on the Leſt; and theſe four Battalions being the firſt that paſſed the River, ſuffered pretty much; of the latter, there were five Officers killed, and eight wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and about ſixty Soldiers killed and wounded. Monſieur <hi>Calimote</hi> followed the Dutch Guards, with his Detachement of 600 Men, whereof mention was made before, and after
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:34476:68"/>them the Regiment <hi>Cambon:</hi> And here it was that Collonel <hi>Calimote</hi> received a Shot, of which he is ſince dead, and ſeveral of his Officers were killed upon the place; Duke <hi>Schonbergh</hi> headed the <hi>Dutch</hi> Foot-Guards, and the King the <hi>Inniskilling</hi> Horſe; telling them, They ſhould be His Guards that Day. Some of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Horſe oppos'd the <hi>Dutch</hi> Foot, who fought up to the middle in Water, and were almoſt born down, before ſome Horſe (which they long called for) could come up to their Relief: In paſſing this Ford, Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> (Famous for the Siege of <hi>Derry</hi>) was killed.</p>
               <p>The Brigade of <hi>Hanmer</hi> paſſed next another Ford, the Count de <hi>Naſſau</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the head of them, as Major-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; and the <hi>Danes</hi> paſſed on their left, Commanded by the Prince of <hi>Wir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tembergh:</hi> After theſe paſſed the Horſe of the left Wing; but in the mean time ſome of the Enemies Squadrons (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned) advanced and Attack'd our Foot: And a Squadron of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies <hi>Guard du Corps,</hi> pierced with great Vigour as far as a little Village where we loſt our great General, his Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg,</hi> who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:34476:69"/>thither to obſerve the Enemies motion. Thoſe that were about his Grace, had before done all they could to perſwade him to retire from thence, but they could not prevail with him. He was killed with a Carbine ſhot, in the Neck, and three Cuts over the Head, and one on his Face. Captain <hi>Foubert,</hi> who was next to him, and had likewiſe received a wound in the Arm, got from his Horſe to help the Duke; but he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed immediately without ſpeaking a word.</p>
               <p>By this time the King had got over the River; who in paſſing it with his Horſe, met with the like oppoſition. The <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Horſe once gave way, but the King went himſelf, and brougt them up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and at the head of the Horſe Charged the Enemy; who after ſome Reſiſtance retired Fighting, Commanded by Lieutenant-General <hi>de la Hoquelle</hi> and Lieutenant-General <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Lauzun</hi> being with the body who made head againſt the Count <hi>de Schon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> the late King <hi>James</hi> himſelf no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Engaging, but ſtanding at the Reer of them, on a riſing Ground, out of harm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way:</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:34476:69"/>
               <p>The Enemy retreated from Defile to Defile; our Horſe purſuing them as far as <hi>Duleek,</hi> where the King, with the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he had with them, joined thoſe of the Count <hi>de Schonberg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Enemy retired about 3 Miles far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and there Poſted themſelves in a very advantageous place; and the King followed them with his Horſe and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, and Orders were given to Attack them there; but it being very late, and the Fight having laſted from 10 in the Morning 'till 9 at Night, his Majeſty did not think fit to engage the Troops any farter, but ordered the Horſe and Dragoons to remain in Arms all Night: He returned to <hi>Duleek,</hi> where the Foot Encampt: But in the Night the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my retired in great Confuſion; We took their Baggage, and eight Pieces of Cannon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> the 2d. the King ſent Monſieur <hi>de la Meliouere,</hi> Brigadier-General, with a Detachment of 300 Foot, and 1000 Horſe, with 8 Pieces of Cannon, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt <hi>Drogheda:</hi> Being arrived there, the Governour receiv'd the firſt Summons with great contempt; but the King ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him Word, That if they forc'd his
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:34476:70"/>Cannon to be Fired on them, he would not give them any Quarter. This ſo frighted the Governour, that having kept the Trumpeter ſome time, he returned Monſier <hi>de la Melionier</hi> this Anſwer; That he would Surrender the Place upon fair Capitulation, <hi>viz.</hi> To march out with Arms and Baggage, Colours Flying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that otherwiſe he would defend the place to the laſt Extremity. <hi>Melonier</hi> ſent him Word, That his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were only to ſuffer them to march out without Arms; and that he muſt quickly reſolve whether he would accept of this Offer. In the mean time Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de la Meloniere</hi> had cauſed two Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries to be raiſed, which would be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the next Morning by break of Day. But the Officers of the Gariſon, after having conſulted together, reſolved to yield; and the Capitulation being Sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they delivered up a Gate, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out about an Hour after, between thirteen and fourteen hundred Men, and were conducted to <hi>Athlone,</hi> the Officers being permitted to wear their Swords. After which, Monſieur <hi>de la Meloniere</hi> gave Protections to a great many <hi>Papiſts,</hi>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:34476:70"/>who expected to have plundered, and marched to join the Army.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Tueſday,</hi> immediately after the Defeat, the Late King <hi>James</hi> Fled to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and came in there about 10 at Night, with about 200 Horſe, all in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order; and about 12, the whole Body of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Horſe came into the City.</p>
               <p>At Five the next Morning, being <hi>Wedneſday, July</hi> the 2d. King <hi>James</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſent for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Lord Mayor, and ſome principal Perſons to the Caſtle, told them, That he found all things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; that in <hi>England</hi> he had an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my which would have Fought, but they proved falſe, and deferted him; That here he had an Army which was Loyal enough, but would ſtand by him: He was now neceſſitated to provide for his ſafey; and that they ſhould make the beſt Terms for themſelves that they could. He told his monial Servants, That he ſhould have now no farther occaſion to keep ſuch a Court as he had done, and that therefore they were at Liberty to diſpoſe of themſelves: He deſired them all to be kind to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, and not to injure them, or this City; for though he quitted it, he did
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:34476:71"/>not quit his Intereſt in it; and ſo with two or three in Company he went to <hi>Bray,</hi> and along by the Sea to <hi>Waterford;</hi> having appointed his Carriages to meet him another way. We hear he did not ſleep 'till he got on Ship-board; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been once driven in again, is ſince clear gon off.</p>
               <p>All this day, being <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> nothing was to be ſeen in <hi>Dublin,</hi> but Officers and Carriages, and the principal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Town, their Wives and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies going away; others coming in duſty and weary, getting away as faſt as they could. About four in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were affrighted with the appearance of the <hi>Iriſh Horſe,</hi> which were drawn out of the City early in the Morning, and which they hoped had been quite gone, entering into Town, followed by the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Foot, in a full Body; but they only marched through the Town to go farther; the Militia that kept the City followed them; only the Governour remained: At laſt he reſolyed to march alſo, and to drive two or three hundred of the principal Priſoners before him; but while they were preparing for this, a falſe Allarm
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:34476:71"/>was ſpread, that a Party of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> being Landed at the Harbour, were juſt at the Towns end; it was too duskie to diſprove this by view, and they had not leiſure to ſend a Meſſenger, but in haſte ſhifted for themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Proteſtants now began to look out, not knowing well in what Condition they were in; but venturing to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, they found Captain <hi>Farlow,</hi> who had been a Priſoner there, keeping Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon alone. Upon this, Captain <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> and ſeveral others, who had been Priſoners, went and ſtayed there all Night; but ſtill they were unſecure, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Arms. Early next Morning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Thurſday,</hi> the Proteſtants ran about to Roman Catholicks Houſes, demanding their Arms, who being quite diſpirited, delivered them without diſpute. By Six in the Morning, the Biſhop of <hi>Meath,</hi> Dr. <hi>King,</hi> and other Principal Proteſtants, form'd a Committee in the Caſtle, and fixed a Proteſtant Militia; and ſent away an Expreſs to the King, of the Towns being at Liberty. This Expreſs found Him Marching up to <hi>Dublin,</hi> in Two Lines, expecting to meet the <hi>Iriſh</hi> at <hi>Swords.</hi> Till Afternoon, this <hi>Thurſday,</hi> the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:34476:72"/>did not hear a Word of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army. But upon the having certain Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Approach of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, the Proteſtants ran about, ſaluting and embracing one an other, and bleſſing God for this Wonderful Deliverance, as if they had been alive from the Dead. At Eight that Night, one Troop of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons came as a Guard to an Officer, that came to take Charge of the Stores. It was impoſſible, the King himſelf coming after this, could be welcomed with equal Joy, as this one Troop; the Proteſtants hung about the Horſes, and were ready to pull the Men off them, as they March'd up to the Caſtle.</p>
               <p>The next Morning, being <hi>Friday, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 4. The Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Overkirk,</hi> came in with Nine Troops of Horſe; and the King being Encamped, by <hi>Finglas,</hi> came on <hi>Sunday</hi> to St. <hi>Patricks</hi> Church, and heard a Sermon, Preached by Dr. <hi>King,</hi> concerning the Power of God; <hi>of which, that which ſeemed to us greateſt upon Earth, mighty Armies, was a faint Shadow.</hi> The King went back to His Camp to Dinner, not ſuffering any Soldiers to come into the City, except a few for Guards.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:34476:72"/>
               <p>By ſome Perſons, in our Army, that have viewed the Dead, at the <hi>Boyne,</hi> I am told, that there was not above Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Hundred Killed, on both Sides, tho perhaps you may hear of greater Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in <hi>England,</hi> which is a wonderful Thing, that ſo ſmall a loſs ſhould diſperſe the whole <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, who ſeemed to be blown away only by a Wind from God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> The Town of <hi>Wexford</hi> Declared for His Majeſty; the Manner of it was thus, Collonel <hi>Butler,</hi> Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the whole County, hearing that the Late King <hi>James</hi> was gone by; on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> laſt, he poſted after Him, and from <hi>Duncannon,</hi> wrote to his Son to come to him, and to follow the Late King <hi>James</hi> to <hi>France:</hi> He wrote alſo another Letter to Captain <hi>Kelly,</hi> to come away with his Company, and to ſet the Caſtle of <hi>Wex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> on Fire, which was under his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; but this Letter falling into the Hands of an Engliſh Merchant, where Collonel <hi>Butler</hi> was Quartered; he did not deliver it, but told the Captain how he was ſent for, concealing that part of the Letter about burning the Caſtle: And ſo ſoon as he and his Company were gone,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:34476:73"/>the Proteſtants there roſe, diſarmed the Papiſts, and ſeized the Caſtle; and at their humble Requeſt, by Two Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, His Majeſty ſent, ſome few Days after, a Regiment, with Arms and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition to ſecure them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The King's Declaration, Pardoning ihe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Commonality. <hi>Cavan</hi> and <hi>Slego,</hi> Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <hi>Lonford,</hi> and Lord <hi>Longford</hi>'s Houſe burnt. Earl <hi>Tyrone</hi> diſplaced at <hi>Waterford,</hi> and <hi>Lacy</hi> made Governour. Four Hundred Head of Cattle taken from the Raparees. <hi>Clonmell</hi> quitted, and <hi>Sarſefield,</hi> with Five Thouſand Men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires from before it, towards <hi>Lymerick. Waterford</hi> Summoned by the King, begins to Capitulate, Surrenders on Articles. Lord <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Howard</hi> Submit. <hi>Lyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> poſſeſſed by the <hi>French.</hi> The King on his way for <hi>England,</hi> alters His Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Captain <hi>Burk</hi> Surrenders <hi>Duncan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. Douglas</hi> and <hi>Kirk,</hi> join the Army. <hi>Yaughal</hi> Surrendred. The Army before <hi>Lymerick.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>JUly</hi> 9. This Morning Early His Majeſty Decamp'd from <hi>Finglas,</hi> to a place
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:34476:73"/>called <hi>Cromlin,</hi> three Miles on the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of <hi>Dublin.</hi> This Day was Publiſhed at the Camp, Their Majeſties Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which follows;</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="royal_declaration">
                  <body>
                     <head>THE <hi>Declaration</hi> OF <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and <hi>MARY,</hi> King and Queen of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> To all the People of the Kingdom of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to whom it may concern.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>William Rex,</signed>
                     </opener>
                     <p>AS it hath pleaſed Almighty God to bleſs Our Arms, in this Kingdom, with a late Victory over our Euemies, at the <hi>Boyne;</hi> and with the Poſſeſſion of Our Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and with the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Oiſperſion of all that did op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:34476:74"/>Vs: VVe are now in ſo happy a proſpect of our Affairs, and of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhing the Rebellion of this Kingdom; That we hold it reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to think of mercy, and to have a Compaſſion upon thoſe whom VVe judge to have been ſeduced; VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, VVe do hereby Declare, VVe ſhall take into Our Royal Protection all poor Labourers, Common Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, Countrey Farmers, Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Cottiers, whatſoever; as alſo, all Citizens, Towns-men, Trades-men, and Artificers, who either remained at Home, or having fled from their Dwellings, ſhall by the Firſt Day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> next, repair to their uſual Places of Abode; Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendering up what Arms they have, to ſuch Iuſtices of the Peace, as are, or ſhall be appointed by Vs, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to receive the ſame, but alſo to Regiſter the Appearance of ſuch of the ſaid Perſons as ſhall come in, and ſubmit to Our Authority. For Our Royal Intention is, and VVe do hereby Declare, That VVe will not only Pardon all thoſe poor Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as to their Lives and Liberties,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:34476:74"/>who ſhall come in by the time aforeſaid, for all Violences they have done or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Command of their Leaders, during the War, but We do promiſe to ſecure them in their Goods, their Stocks of Cattle, and all their Chattels perſonal whatſoever, Willing and Requiring them to come in; and where they were Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, there to preſerve the Harveſt of Graſs and Corn for the ſupply of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But foraſmuch as many of them had a legal Right to the Tenancy of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Lands, ſome holden from <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> and ſome held from <hi>Popiſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors,</hi> who have been concerned in the the Rebellion agaiuſt us: Our Will and Pleaſure is, that all thoſe Tenants who held from Our good <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects, do pay their Rents to their reſpective Landlords: And that the Tenants of all thoſe who have been concerned in the preſent Rebellion againſt us, do keep their Rent in their hands until they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice from the Commiſſioners of Our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, unto whom they are to account for the ſame. And as we do hereby ſtrictly forbid all Violence, Rapine, and Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, to any who ſhall thus come in, and remain Obedient to us; ſo for thoſe of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34476:75"/>this, or any other Rank or Quality, who are already in Our Quarters, and within our Power, and Obedient to Vs, We do hereby charge and require that they be not moleſted in any ſort, without Our particular Command. For the deſperate Leaders of the preſent Rebellion, who have violated thoſe Laws, by which this Kingdom is united, and inſeperably an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> who have called in the <hi>French,</hi> who have Authorized all Violences and Depredations againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and who rejected the Gracious Pardon We offered them in Our Proclamation of the Twenty ſecond of <hi>February, 1688.</hi> As We are now, by <hi>God's</hi> great Favour, in condition to make them ſenſible of their Errors, ſo are We reſolved to leave them to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of War, unleſs by great and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt demonſtrations, We ſhall be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced they deſerve Our Mercy, which We ſhall never refuſe, to thoſe who are truly Penitent.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given at Our Royal Camp at <hi>Finglaſs,</hi> near <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                           <date>the ſeventh day of <hi>July,</hi> 1690. In the Second Year of Our Reign.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:34476:75"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 11. The King ſet out from <hi>Cromlin</hi> to <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> with a part of his Army; General <hi>Douglas,</hi> with another part, went ſome days before towards <hi>Athlone;</hi> and a third by way of <hi>Bray,</hi> towards <hi>Wexford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 14. His Majeſty Encamped at <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> 21 Miles from <hi>Dublin,</hi> where News was brought to the Camp, That <hi>Cavan</hi> and <hi>Sligoe</hi> had voluntarily Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred; and that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Villains, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Raparees, had Burnt <hi>Longford,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Longford</hi>'s Houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 15. His Majeſty, with the Army, Encamped at <hi>Caſtle-Dermote.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the <hi>16th,</hi> We Marched to <hi>Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lough,</hi> which was but five Miles.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>17th,</hi> We Encamped about <hi>Kells,</hi> leaving the Road to <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> that City being above four Miles out of our way; here, by ſome Deſerters come into our Camp, we underſtood, That the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> (who, ſince King <hi>James</hi>'s leaving of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſtiles himſelf, Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland</hi>) having ſome Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> Governor of <hi>Waterford,</hi> ſent for him to <hi>Lymerick,</hi> and made Old Colonel <hi>Lacy</hi> Governor in his ſtead, and that the Enemy had in it about 1600 Men. Colonel <hi>Eppinger,</hi> who was
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:34476:76"/>ſent from <hi>Dublin,</hi> with a ſmall Party, by Sea, towards <hi>Wexford</hi> (that being Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as you have heard) took Poſſeſſion of the Place, and ſecured a Garriſon in it; he ſound a conſiderable quantity of Proviſions there, and his Men, a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, took 400 Head of Cattle from the Raparees, who had taken them a little time before from the Country People, on whom they have, ever ſince the Battle at the <hi>Boyne,</hi> committed many Outrages, and done much Miſchief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 19. We came to a place called <hi>Bennets-bridge,</hi> within 16 Miles of <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> where we Encamped. Here we underſtood, that on the <hi>18th</hi> the Enemy quitted <hi>Clonmel,</hi> notwithſtanding it is a very conſiderable Paſs, lately ſtrengthned by the addition of ſeveral new Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Major General <hi>Sarsfield</hi> was Poſted there with 5000 <hi>Iriſh;</hi> but on the approach of our Army in its Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, he retired towards <hi>Lymerick.</hi> This day four <hi>French</hi> Officers came over to us, they give an account, That the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> and the Count <hi>De Lauſun</hi> are Fortifying of <hi>Lymerick,</hi> the remains of the Army being in that Neighbourhood, but in a very ill condition, having loſt all
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34476:76"/>their Baggage. This day His Majeſty Dined with the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> at the Caſtle of <hi>Kilkenny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the <hi>20th,</hi> We Decamped from <hi>Bennets-Bridge,</hi> and marched about ſeven Miles, to a place called <hi>Roſſen-narrow,</hi> and the next day we came to <hi>Carick.</hi> His Majeſty commanded a Trumpet to be ſent to Summon <hi>Waterford,</hi> requiring them to Surrender the Place: They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired time till the next Morning, when they ſent out Articles, but the King not approving thereof, let them know, that they ſhould go out with their own Arms and Baggage only, and that if they did not accept thereof, but ſtayed till they were Attacked, he would give them no Quarter. However they ſent ſome of their Scruples again the next day, and Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> was ſent thither with five Regiments, and ſeveral Pieces of Cannon, to anſwer them; the next day in the Afternoon, the Capitulations were Signed, and the next day after, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon Marched out with their Arms and Baggage, the number of 1600, and were conducted to <hi>Mallow,</hi> 12 Miles in their way to <hi>Lymerick:</hi> The Garriſon would not have had ſo good Terms, only His
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:34476:77"/>Majeſty had Compaſſion on 300 <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Families in the Town. Several of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Officers ſtaid behind in the Town, and prayed His Majeſties Protection. The ſame day, the Lord <hi>Dover,</hi> and Lord <hi>George Howard,</hi> with ſeveral others, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelves to the King. The Garriſon of <hi>Athlone,</hi> upon the approach of Lieutenant General <hi>Douglas,</hi> broke down their Bridge, Burnt part of the Town, and retired into the Caſtle. The <hi>French,</hi> when they firſt came to <hi>Lymerick,</hi> took Poſſeſſion of it with their Infantry, under the Command of the Count <hi>De Lauſun,</hi> and they would not ſuffer any <hi>Iriſh</hi> to come into the Town, but turned out the Garriſon they found there; ſo that the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> and General <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> with their <hi>Iriſh,</hi> were forced all to Encamp without the Town.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 25. The King viewed the Walls of <hi>Waterford,</hi> without entring into the Town, and returned back to the Camp, which was about Three Miles diſtant, where all things were ready for an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack. His Majeſty Dined in the Camp, and then returned to <hi>Carick</hi> that Night. From <hi>Waterford</hi> His Majeſty ſent a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to the Governor of <hi>Duncannon</hi>-Fort,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:34476:77"/>Captain <hi>Michael Burk,</hi> offering the ſame Capitulation which had been grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Waterford,</hi> and letting him know, if he refuſed, or delayed to comply, he muſt expect no Mercy. He inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſix days, to conſult the Lord <hi>Tyrcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,</hi> which being refuſed, he declared he would take that time, whereupon the Cannon was ordered down, in order to an Attack; but the next day, being the <hi>26th</hi> in the Evening, Sir <hi>Cloudſly Shovel,</hi> appearing with 16 Frigates in view, it ſo terriſied them, that the Governor wrote to Major General <hi>Kirk,</hi> that they would accept of what had been offered; which His Majeſty being made acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, he was pleaſed to Order, That they ſhould ſtill have the benefit of the Articles that were at firſt propoſed, and the Fort was accordingly Surrendred, whereby we are poſſeſſed of a very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Poſt, which commands the River of <hi>Waterford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the 27. His Majeſty left the Camp, and ſet forward for <hi>Dublin,</hi> reſolving to return immediately for <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the 29. The King arrived at <hi>Chapple-Izod.</hi> His Majeſty having reſolved to Beſiege <hi>Lymerick,</hi> where the Enemy have
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:34476:78"/>drawn what force they can together, ſent Order to Lieutenant General <hi>Douglas</hi> to March from <hi>Athlone,</hi> and joyn the Count <hi>De Solmes;</hi> and the better to diſpoſe of things for the puſhing on the Siege, His Majeſty altered His Reſolutions of going immediately for <hi>England,</hi> and put off His Journey for ſome time.</p>
               <p>On the 27. We Marched from <hi>Carick,</hi> under the Command of the Count <hi>De Solmes;</hi> His Majeſty, as aforementioned, being gone for <hi>Dublin,</hi> and came this day to the Town of <hi>Clonmel,</hi> which is Eight very long Miles; this Place ſeems to be very ſtrongly ſituated, and doubtleſs might have held out for ſome time, had it been Garriſoned by any but <hi>Iriſh</hi> Men. The 28. We Marched ſeven Miles farther; And the next day, being the <hi>29th.</hi> We Encamped at a place called <hi>Goolin-Bridge,</hi> which is about 23 Miles from <hi>Lymerick:</hi> Here, as ſoon as we arrived, we had the confirmation, that the <hi>French</hi> had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed themſelves of the City of <hi>Lymerick,</hi> and that they would not ſuffer any of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces to come into it, having turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out thoſe few that were in Garriſon there.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:34476:78"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> the firſt, Some Parties of Horſe marched from our Camp, and advanced within ſight of the Enemy at <hi>Lymerick,</hi> who, on the approach of theſe advanced Parties, were in great conſternation; and they brought us word, that the groſs of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, conſiſting of about 25000 Men, were (upon the hearing of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of our Army) retired from beyond the <hi>Shannon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>August</hi> 2. Advice was brought into the Camp, of the Surrender of the Town of <hi>Youghal,</hi> the manner as follows:</p>
               <p>The Garriſon that Marched from <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford,</hi> according to their Articles of Capitulation, were conducted as far as the Town of <hi>Youghal,</hi> which is about 14 Miles, by 50 of Colonel <hi>Leviſon</hi>'s Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, under the Command of one Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Pownal,</hi> who having ſome Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with the Governor of the Place (who was before Governor of <hi>Carick-fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi>) he told him the certain ruine he would bring upon himſelf and Garriſon, if he thought of holding out, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adviſing him to Surrender; the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor deſired he would wait his Anſwer till Ten at Night, at which time, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:34476:79"/>he Marched out with Three Companies of Foot, and gave him Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Town: Captain <hi>Pownal</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entered, having firſt ſearched for Mines, found in the Place 14 Cannon mounted, and two without Carriages, (but neither Powder nor Ball) 350 Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of Oats, 215 Stone of Wool, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other ſorts of Proviſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> the third, A Deſerter came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Camp from <hi>Lymerick,</hi> and told us, That yeſterday Morning, the ſecond In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, he ſaw the <hi>French</hi> March out of Town with Eight Field-Pieces; and that the common report was, That they were going to <hi>Galway,</hi> to Embark there for <hi>France,</hi> that being a more convenient Port for their taking Shipping than <hi>Lyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick; Galway</hi> being but Nine Miles from the Mouth of the Bay, and <hi>Lymerick</hi> is Sixty: And that as ſoon as the <hi>French</hi> had quitted the Place, and were march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, the Three Regiments of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> under the Command of one Colonel <hi>Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terel,</hi> marched in, and took Poſſeſſion of it. He could not tell the certain number of the <hi>French</hi> Ships that were in the River of <hi>Lymerick,</hi> but ſays, he ſaw only Three
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:34476:79"/>Proviſion-Ships at the Key; and that the Rebels in the Place were very much diſheartened, being in little hopes of farther Supply. The Regiments, that were ſent to Reduce the Town of <hi>Waterford,</hi> and Fort of <hi>Duncannon,</hi> under the Command of Major General <hi>Kirk,</hi> joyned us on <hi>Saturday;</hi> and Lieutenant General <hi>Douglas</hi> lies Encamped within Five Miles of us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> 5. An Account was brought to the Camp, That a mixt Body of the Enemies, and Rabble Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parees together, were gone from the County of <hi>Cork,</hi> to Plunder the Town of <hi>Youghal,</hi> which a Troop of our Dragoon; lately poſſeſs'd themſelves of; upon which, befides ſome Companies of Foot that were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thither ſome days ſince, a Detachment of Six hundred Horſe, from our Camp, are ſent to oppoſe them.</p>
               <p>On the 6. We Decamped from <hi>Coolen-Bridge,</hi> and Marched in Two Bodies towards <hi>Lymerick,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry taking their way by a place called <hi>Sallaweed,</hi> and the Chavalry by <hi>Cullen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the 7. We came to <hi>Carickelliſh,</hi> which is Six Miles from <hi>Lymerick;</hi> and here our Horſe and Foot joyned in one Body again; and in the Evening ſome ſmall Detached Parties were ſent to obſerve the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture and Motions of the Enemy; but, on the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of our Men, the Enemy retired in great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitation from place to place, and in the Night burnt a great many ſmall Houſes and Cabbins within Three Miles of the Town.</p>
               <p>On the 8. At One in the Morning, His Majeſty ſent out Nine hundred Horſe, and Two hundred Foot, under the Command of the Earl of <hi>Portland,</hi> and Brigadeer <hi>Stewart,</hi> &amp;c. who advanced within Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non-Shot of the Town, notwithſtanding the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition made by Three Regiments of the Enemies Foot, one of Horſe, and another of Dragoons, who ſtood
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:34476:80"/>but one Firing, tho' they had the covert of the Hedges; through which they Fired. About Four hours after, this Detachment returned to our Camp, and gave the King an account of the Poſture the Enemy were in: And about Seven a Clock His Majeſty went him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a freſh Party of 200 ſelect Horſe, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached within Two Miles of the Town.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 9. At Five this Morning our whole Army Decamped, Colonel <hi>Earl</hi> leading the Van with 200 Horſe, and 1000 Choſen Foot. Upon our approach we found the Enemy drawn up within Two Miles of the City of <hi>Lymerick;</hi> their Horſe made a ſhew of Reſiſtance, and ſtood our firſt Charge, but ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards gave way, when they threw themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Hedges, and Fired ſo from thence, that our Horſe could not come to them: Upon which we brought ſome ſmall Field Pieces to Fire upon them, and about One a Clock Colonel <hi>Earl</hi> Attacked them with his Foot, who run on with that Bravery, tho' the Enemy made a great Fire through the Hedges, that within Two hours time they poſſeſſed themſelves of Two advantagious Poſts, called <hi>Ireton Fort,</hi> and the <hi>Old Kirk.</hi> Then the Beſieged began to Fire from the Town with their great Guns, which killed us ſome Men, but in all this days Action we had not above 35 Killed and Wounded, tho' above 250 of the Enemy were killed in their ſeveral Retreats, among which were ſeveral Officers of Note. Betwixt ſix and ſeven in the Evening His Majeſty ordered a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter to be ſent with a Summons to the Town. The Trumpeter was ſent back with this Anſwer from Monſieur <hi>Boiſeleau</hi> the Governor, <hi>That as King</hi> James <hi>had intrusted him with that Garriſon, he would recommend himſelf to the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>by a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Defence.</hi> About Eight at Night the King went to his Camp, having been on Horſeback from
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:34476:80"/>Four in the Morning, giving the neceſſary Orders, and expoſing himſelf amidſt the greateſt of Dangers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 10. Early this Morning Lieutenant General <hi>Gnikle,</hi> and Major General <hi>Kirk,</hi> with 5000 Horſe, Foot and Dragoons, Marched over the Ford at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naghbeg,</hi> a place about Two Miles above the Town, where 11 of the Enemies Regiments of Horſe and Foot were ready to maintain the Paſs, but when our Forces came, they found the Enemy had quitted their Station, having retired in the Night; here our Foot were forced to wade up to the middle in Water. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Eight the King went over in Perſon, and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Three Regiments of Foot, with ſome Pieces of Cannon to be Poſted there.</p>
               <p>The 11. was ſpent in viſiting the ſeveral Poſts, and giving the neceſſary Orders about the Siege.</p>
               <p>The 12. His Majeſty Commanded Brigadeer <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art,</hi> with a Detachment, and Four Pieces of Cannon, to go early this Morning and Attack Caſtle <hi>Connel,</hi> which is of conſiderable Strength, ſcituated on the <hi>Shannon,</hi> about Four Miles from <hi>Lymerick:</hi> There were in it above 140 Men, Commanded by Captain <hi>Barnwel,</hi> who had refuſed to Surrender upon the Summons ſent him the Night before, but no ſooner ſaw the Cannon but ſubmitted at Diſcretion. The ſame day fell out the unhappy accident of ſurpriſing our Cannon by <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> who burſt Two of them. This accident hindred us ſeveral days in our carrying on the Siege of <hi>Lymerick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the 14. An Expreſs came to our Camp from <hi>Youghal,</hi> giving an account, That the Garriſon there conſiſting of 50 Foot, and 36 Dragoons, hearing what miſchief the Raparees did near the <hi>Castle-Martyr;</hi> the Officers that Commanded drew out both the Horſe and Foot, and Marched to Attack them, but the Foot not being able to March ſo faſt
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:34476:81"/>as the Dragoons, the latter met near <hi>Caſtle-Martyr</hi> 300 Rapparees, Horſe and Foot, and immediately Routed them, killing 60, and taking 17 Priſoners, and the Foot being come up, they Summoned the Caſtle, which Surrendred upon liberty to go to <hi>Cork.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> 16. This Morning was Publiſhed a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation in behalf of the Clergy and their Tythes; and moſt part of the day was ſpent in concerting Matters abous the Siege of <hi>Lymerick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the 17. The whole day was ſpent in making the neceſſary Preparations, and getting all things ready for the opening of the Trenches which in the Evening was put in Execution; the Trenches were opened with ſeveral Battalions, conſiſting of <hi>Engliſh, French,</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Infantry, Commanded by the Generals, Prince <hi>Wirtemberg, Kirk, Petteau,</hi> and <hi>Bellaſis.</hi> We advanced this Night about 300 Paces, and took Two Redoubts from the Enemy; from whence they might have diſturbed our Work-men.</p>
               <p>The 18. About Ten at Night, the Trenches were Relieved by Lieutenant General <hi>Douglas,</hi> my Lord <hi>Sidney,</hi> and Count <hi>Naſſau,</hi> with 7 Battallions of Foot; and this Night we made our regular approaches towards another ſtrong Redoubt of the Enemies.</p>
               <p>The 19. The Trenches were Relieved by the Pr. of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> Maj. Gen. <hi>Kirk, Petteau,</hi> and Sir <hi>H. Bellaſis,</hi> Brigadeer, and we continued our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches towards the ſaid Redoubt, which the King gave orders ſhould be Attackt the next day.</p>
               <p>The 20. The Trenches were Relieved by Lieut. Gen. <hi>Douglas, Sidney, Naſſau,</hi> and <hi>Stewart;</hi> the Signal was given by Three Guns, about Two in the Afternoon, when our Men that were Detached for this Service to the Number of 150 (choice ſelect Men) beſides Officers, immediately fell on, and with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Courage entred the Fort, and drave out
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:34476:81"/>the Enemy, killing about Forty of them.</p>
               <p>The 21. We carried on our Trenches, and finiſhed them to that degree, ſo as to hinder any more Sallies.</p>
               <p>The 22. We raiſed a Battery of Eight Guns, and 24 pound Ball, and Two of 18, againſt the Enemies high Towers, from whence they Fired upon our Men, and we have quite levelled them.</p>
               <p>The 23. This Morning one of <hi>Gilmoy</hi>'s Troopers came over to us, and brought with him a Boy and Four good Horſes. This Afternoon we Played fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly into the Town with our Bombs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Fired the Town in ſeveral places, one fell into their great Magazine of Hay, which was conſumed, and ſeveral Houſes burnt, the Fire laſting there about ſix hours; another ſet Fire to a place near the Church, which was not conſumed till Five the next Morning, and as that was quenched, we Fired another place, which was Blown up by the Enemy.</p>
               <p>The 24. This Morning our Guns Fired very brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the Walls, but being too far off did little Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, ſo that Two new Batteries were this day made, within Eighty Paces of the Wall, and our Trenches were carried on within Piſtol-ſhot of the Counterſcarp; and our Guns were carried this Night down to the ſaid Batteries, firſt againſt the Wall of Eight half Cannon; the other of Two 18 Pounders, againſt the <hi>Kings-Iſland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 25. This Morning, about break of day, we began to Fire from our new Batteries againſt the Wall, but it Rained ſo hard till Three in the Afternoon, that our Men could not work the Guns; however, on any intermiſſion of the Rain, our Guns play'd violently againſt the walls and from Three, we Fired at leaſt 300 Shot, with good Succeſs againſt the Walls.</p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:34476:82"/>
               <p>The 26. We widened the Breach we had made the day before in the Wall of the Town, and beat down part of the Enemies Palliſado's on the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcarp. This Night we ſet Fire to the Town again, which Burnt very vehemently.</p>
               <p>The 27. The King ordered an Attack to be made on the Counterſcarp, which was begun about Three in the Afternoon; a Detached Party of Granadeers made the onſet, and was ſeconded by other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachments, who went on with that Heat and Courage, that having gained the Counterſcarp, and a Fort which the Enemy had under the Walls, inſtead of lodging themſeves there, as they were ordered to do, they mounted the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarp, following the <hi>Iriſh</hi> that fled that way, and ſome were entring into the Town; but the Enemy being intrenched behind the Breach, and having Planted Cannon againſt it, they were cut off. The Fight laſted Three hours, during which the Enemy were ſtill ſupplied with freſh Men. What Men we have loſt in theſe ſeveral Actions we cannot preciſely ſay, but by the beſt computation its thought we may have loſt about 700 killed and wounded, during the beginning of the Siege.</p>
               <p>The 28. At Night we advanced our Trenches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 yards, notwithſtanding it had Rained moſt part of the day; it continued to Rain all this Night, and all the next Day to the 30<hi>th,</hi> almoſt without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion; ſo that our M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n waded above their mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the Trenches: On which, after a Council of War being called, His Majeſty thought fit to give Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the raiſing the Siege.</p>
               <p>The 30. In the Afternoon the Cannon and heavy Baggage were ſent from the Camp.</p>
               <p>On the 31. Five Thouſand Horſe being ordered for a Reer-Guard to Repreſs any Sallies, the whole
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:34476:82"/>Army Decamped, and marched off in very good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and without any diſturbance from the Enemy, towards <hi>Clonmel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1, 2, 3, and 4. The Army, with the Artillery, continued in their motion, taking very ſlow Marches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 5. We came to <hi>Typerary,</hi> which is about Twenty Miles from <hi>Lymerick.</hi> His Majeſty having given the neceſſary Orders, diſpoſed the Army, and named the Lord Viſcount <hi>Sidney,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningsby,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> to be Lords Juſtices of <hi>Ireland,</hi> left the Camp very early in the Morning, accompanied with the Prince of <hi>Denmark</hi> to <hi>Waterford,</hi> and Dined with Colonel <hi>Brewer,</hi> the Governor; and, in the Afternoon, the Wind proving fair, they Embarked at <hi>Duncannon</hi>-Fort, and immediately Sailed out of the Bay, accompanied with Two Men of War, Three Yatches, and ſeveral ſmall Tenders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Septemb.</hi> 6. This day ſeveral Regiments of Horſe and Foot, under the Command of Lieutenant General <hi>Douglas,</hi> Marched from the Camp, towards the <hi>North.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 7. Monſieur <hi>Forreſt</hi> went this Morning with 900 Horſe and Foot, and Four Cannon, and took a conſiderable Poſt called <hi>Kilmalock,</hi> which intercepts the Paſſage betwixt <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>Lymerick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12. We lay quiet in our Camp, and nothing of moment occurred.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 13. This Morning the Major General <hi>Scrave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> and <hi>Teteau,</hi> Marched from our Camp with 3000 Horſe and Foot towards <hi>Mallow.</hi> The Deſerters that came into our Camp laſt Night, aſſured us, That the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were falling into miſerable Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that they are divided amongſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept</hi> 14. Early this Morning we Decamped under the Command of our General, the Count <hi>De Solmes,</hi>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:34476:83"/>and Marched to a place call'd <hi>Caſhil,</hi> the See of an Arch-Biſhop, near which place we Encamped.</p>
               <p>The next day, being the <hi>15th,</hi> an Account was brought from a Captain in Colonel <hi>Leviſon</hi>'s Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, that he had, with his Troop, fallen upon 1400 Rapparees, that were coming from <hi>Cork</hi> to <hi>Liſmore,</hi> and that he had killed 40, and taken 3 Priſoners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 16. Early this Morning 100 Detached Horſe were ſent out to look after a Party of Rapparees, who had killed three of our Forragers in this Neighbourhood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 17. This day it was confirmed by ſeveral Perſons that came to our Camp from <hi>Lymerick,</hi> That the <hi>French</hi> are all gone from <hi>Galway,</hi> and that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are in a very ill condition, not knowing how to Subſiſt this Winter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 18. This day advice came to our Camp, That Major General <hi>Scravemore</hi> and <hi>Teteau,</hi> who Marched from hence on the <hi>13th</hi> Inſtant, with 2000 Horſe and Foot from <hi>Typerary,</hi> ſent Colonel <hi>Donep</hi> with a Detachment to Burn the Bridge of <hi>Malla,</hi> and to view the Caſtle, which having performed, he returned to the Generals the <hi>17th.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 20. <hi>Sarsfield</hi> having paſſed the <hi>Shannon</hi> with Fourteen Regiments of Horſe, Foot, and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, and Three Field Pieces, Marched to <hi>Bir,</hi> an open Village, and Attacked Sir <hi>L. Parſons</hi> Houſe, in which were Eighty Men, who Fired ſo briskly, that they killed about 100 of the Enemy; upon which, and the news of the approach of our Forces, under the Command of Lieutenant General <hi>Douglas,</hi> and Sir <hi>J. Lanier,</hi> they retired in diſorder. This Afternoon the Count <hi>De Solmes,</hi> our General, left the Camp, and is gone to <hi>Dublin,</hi> in his way to <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:34476:83"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 21. This Morning Two Perſons came into our Camp from <hi>Galway,</hi> who confirm the former Account we had of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> and <hi>Lauſun</hi>'s being gone off with the <hi>French</hi> Forces for <hi>France,</hi> of whom divers are left Sick in the Suburbs of that Place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 22. This Morning Advice was brought to the Camp, That (yeſterday being the <hi>21ſt</hi>) the Earl of <hi>Marlborough,</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces, and the whole Fleet, arrived before the Harbour of <hi>Cork,</hi> where they Anchored. Upon which, Major General <hi>Scravemore</hi> and <hi>Teteau,</hi> Marched to joyn them with 1200 Horſe and Dragoons, and Two Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallions of <hi>Danes,</hi> who were followed by ſome <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here we ſhall leave the Camp at <hi>Caſhil,</hi> and give an account of the Actions of the Army, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Earl of <hi>Marlborough</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 23. This day the greateſt part of the Army Landed at <hi>Paſſage,</hi> between Four and Five in the Morning, and the reſt in the Afternoon, and at the ſame time the light Artillery were put on Shore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 24. About Six hundred Seamen, Gunners, and Carpenters voluntary went on Shore, and were immediately Detached to be imployed in Mounting and Placing the Cannon to Batter the Town; and the whole Army Marched, and Encamped within a Mile and half of the Town: And this Evening 1000 Men were Detached, and ordered to poſſeſs themſelves of ſeveral advantagious Poſts, within Muſquet ſhot of the Town, which the Enemy, upon their approach, ſoon quitted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 25. This day the Camp advanced within Muſquet-ſhot of the <hi>South,</hi> and the <hi>Danes</hi> did the like on the <hi>North.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 26. we advanced our Guards into the Ruines of the Suburbs, and played upon the <hi>Old Fort,</hi> from Two Batteries.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:34476:84"/>
               <p>The 27. We made a Breach in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> part of the Wall, from a Battery of Two 24 Pounders, and Three of 18 Pounders. Towards the Evening the Enemy beat a Parly, and ſent out an Officer to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulate, and Hoſtages were exchanged, but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy not agreeing to the Terms propoſed.</p>
               <p>The 28. In the Morning Four Regiments were appointed under the Command of Brigadeer <hi>Churchil,</hi> to paſs over to an Iſland lying near the Wall, where the Breach was made, which they performed with great Courage, paſſing through the Water which at low Ebb was up to their Arm-pits. The Granadeers Commanded by the Lord <hi>Colcheſter;</hi> having the Van, Marched forward, expoſed to all the Enemies Fire, through the Iſland, within 20 yards of the Wall of the Town, and poſſeſſed themſelves of an Houſe under the Wall The Volunteers who went on with this firſt Detachment, were the Duke of <hi>Grafton</hi> (who was Mortally Wounded) the Lord <hi>O Bryon,</hi> Colonel <hi>Greenvile,</hi> the Captains <hi>Cornwal, Leighton, Neville, Fairbone,</hi> and ſeveral other Sea Officers. Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after this, the Enemy beat a Parley, but my Lord <hi>Marleborough</hi> would not allow them any other Conditions than to be Priſoners of War, which they yielded to; and the Capitulation was Signed. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the ſame Night 200 Men entred into the <hi>Old Fort,</hi> which is very Strong: And this Morning, being the <hi>29th,</hi> we took Poſſeſſion of the Town. The Garriſon which conſiſted of between 4 and 5000 Men, being made Priſoners of War. We have not loſt in all this Siege above Fifty Men, and ſome few Wounded.</p>
               <p>Immediately after the Articles of <hi>Cork</hi> was Signed, 500 Horſe was ſent with a Summons to <hi>Kin-ſale,</hi> upon the appearance of whom, the Governor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently gave Orders to ſet Fire to the Town in ſeveral
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:34476:84"/>parts; which as ſoon as done, they all ran to the <hi>Old Fort;</hi> but our Men eſpying it, got in and quenched it before it had Burnt one Houſe; after which, the <hi>Old Fort</hi> was Summoned to Surrender, but the Governor returned Anſwer, <hi>That he would Defend it to the laſt Man.</hi> Upon which an account was ſent to the Earl of <hi>Marleborough</hi> to acquaint him with the State of things; who Marched with the reſt of the Forces, <hi>Octob.</hi> 1. from <hi>Cork</hi> to <hi>Five Mile Bridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 2. The Earl of <hi>Marleborough,</hi> &amp;c. Arriv'd before <hi>Kin-ſale,</hi> and towards the Evening the Forces Encamped, and took their Poſts about the <hi>New Fort;</hi> and Major General <hi>Teteau</hi> was ordered with 800 Men to Attack the <hi>Old Fort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 3. The Major General having paſſed the River in the Night, a little after Day-break he Storm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Fort, making a ſhew of Attacking it where it was weakeſt; while in the mean time he cauſed a Detachment to make an Aſſault in another place, where the Enemy leaſt apprehended it, which ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo well, that our Men all at once gained the little Baſtions. At the ſame time ſeveral Barrels of Powder took Fire, and blew up Fifty of the Enemy. Inſtead of 150 we found in it 450 Men, of whom about 220 were killed and blown up, and the reſt made Priſoners of War. The Governor, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Officers were found Slain upon the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts. Our Soldiers got a great deal of Plunder. My Lord <hi>Marleborough</hi> then ſent a Summons to the <hi>New Fort,</hi> who anſwered, <hi>That it would be time enough to Capitulate a Month hence,</hi> upon which, my Lord ordered Batteries to be raiſed againſt it; and on the <hi>5th</hi> we opened our Trenches, and on the <hi>9th</hi> had advanced them to the Counterſcarp, but the ill Weather hindred the coming up of our Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:34476:85"/>till the <hi>11th,</hi> when part of it arrived. The <hi>12th</hi> in the Morning Six Pieces were Mounted at the <hi>Danes</hi> Atrack, and Two Mortars at the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which Fired all that day.</p>
               <p>The <hi>13th,</hi> Two 24 Pounders were placed on the ſame Battery: The <hi>Danes,</hi> on their ſide, had made a reaſonable Breach, and the Night following, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Enemy, they made a falſe Attack.</p>
               <p>The <hi>15th</hi> the Cannon continued to Play all the Morning, and every thing was prepared to have laid our Galleries over the Ditch, but at One a Clock the Enemy beat a Parley, and deſired Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges might be exchanged, which being done, the Articles of Surrender were agreed on, and Signed about Midnight, by which the middle Baſtion was to be delivered up the next Morning; and the Garriſon, conſiſting of about 1200 Men, Marched out the next day after with their Arms and Baggage, and to be conducted to <hi>Lymerick.</hi> We have had in the Attack of this Place about 250 Men killed and wounded.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
